<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Souldiery spiritualized, or, The Christian souldier orderly and strenously engaged in the spiritual warre and so fighting the good fight represented in a sermon preached at Boston in New England on the day of the artillery election there, June 1, 1674 / by Joshua Moodey ...</title>
            <author>Moodey, Joshua, 1633?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W3526</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13540355</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13540355</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100070</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51206)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100070)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 796:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Souldiery spiritualized, or, The Christian souldier orderly and strenously engaged in the spiritual warre and so fighting the good fight represented in a sermon preached at Boston in New England on the day of the artillery election there, June 1, 1674 / by Joshua Moodey ...</title>
                  <author>Moodey, Joshua, 1633?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Green,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, IX, 26 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100070:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100070:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LDIERY SPIRIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALIZED,</hi> OR <hi>the CHRISTIAN SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LDIER Orderly, and Strenuouſly Engaged in the</hi> SPIRITUAL WARRE. <hi>And SO fighting the good Fight:</hi> Repreſented in a SERMON Preached at BOSTON in <hi>NEW ENGLAND</hi> on the Day of the ARTIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LERY <hi>ELECTION</hi> there, <hi>June</hi> 1. 1674.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>A MOODEY</hi> Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Portsmouth</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>1 Tim. 6. 12.</bibl>
            <q>Fight the good fight of Faith.</q>
            <bibl>2 Tim. 2. 3.</bibl>
            <q>Thou therefore endure hardneſs, as a good Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</q>
            <bibl>Ver. 5.</bibl>
            <q>And if a Man alſo ſtrive for Maſteries, yet is he not Crowned except he ſtrive lawfully.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE:</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Green.</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100070:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100070:2"/>
            <head>To the much Honoured, the Artillery Company in BOSTON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured and Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Enſuing Word is the Lords, is Mine, is Yours, and is to be lookt at as a Meſſage from the Lord, by me, to your ſelves, (to your ſelves I ſay, nextly and immediately, yet not ſo reſtrictively, but that all others in like capacity with your ſelves; yea all <hi>Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> into whoſe hands it ſhall come, may look at themſelves as concerned therein)</p>
            <p>It is the Lords as part of his Counſel, Mind and Will: ſome of the great things of Gods Law lately Preached, now written to you.</p>
            <p>It is mine, as an Inſtrument (however <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nworthy) in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ompoſing, then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing, now publiſhing of the ſame.</p>
            <p>It is yours, as I was called by you to this work, a Servant to you therein, and as by this preſentation it is now made more eſpecially yours.</p>
            <p>As the Lords, you are moſt ſolemnly Commanded; as mine, moſt humbly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated; as your own, ſtrongly obliged to peruſe, understand, receive and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe what is hereſent you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> could not think any thing of mine worthy of the publick view; but ſeeing your ſelves thought otherwiſe, and others, whom I honour and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verence were like minded with your ſelves; I thought meet to ſubmit to perſons of better judgements. And therefore have permitted it to paſs the Preſs, being not able to be inexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Importunity of my Friends, nor daring to be diſobedient to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of my Superiours, and the deſires of Superiours (in Caſe, and in this Caſe) I account Commands.</p>
            <p>The Lord expected that all the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> ſhould contribute ſomething toward the <hi>building of the Tabernacle;</hi> and that none might plead Pover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y as an Argument for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Exemption, ordered their bringing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed his accepting of <hi>Goats Hair</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> as well as <hi>ſilk and ſilver, Chittim Wood</hi> as well as <hi>precious Stones, (ſee</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od. 25. 1-8) <hi>I</hi> was thence encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to bring my Oblation, when called for, of what was under my Hand. He that ha's received but one Talent must lay it out, not wrap it up. The Lord is no hard Maſter, he accepts according to what a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, not what he hath not, (<hi>2 Cor. 8. 12.</hi>) and men ſhould do the like. If what is here done may (though but in the leaſt degree) promote the work of the Lords houſe among you, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, I ſhall attain my End, and be abundantly rewarded for my Labour.</p>
            <p>If any that were mine Auditors ſhould object the difference between the
<pb facs="tcp:100070:3"/> Sermon as then preached and now written. I muſt own it, and add that it was of fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, not choice, my Memory not ſerving me at any Time to Remember Words, nor at all Times things in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. You have it in the Preſs a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was intended for the Pulpit, and at you ſhould have had it there (at leaſt for the Subſtance) if I could.</p>
            <p>As for my manner of ſpeaking in he uſing of many <hi>Metaphorical Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>Alluſions</hi> unto the <hi>Calling, Poſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> and <hi>motions</hi> of <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and this often in your moſt common and <hi>familiar Terms</hi> and <hi>Phraſes,</hi> though it may poſſibly grate upon ſome <hi>Critical</hi> and <hi>captious Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> yet I hope it will be at leaſt <hi>excuſable</hi> or <hi>tolerable</hi> to your ſelves, It being done chiefly for your ſakes. My aim being to <hi>Spirituali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> your <hi>Calling</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el you a littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of that <hi>much</hi> of Heaven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is therein contained, I had no readier way b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore me to do it then this. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndle the ſame <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>Divinity</hi> on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion and befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>other Audi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory, I could and ſhould have ſought out other words, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t matters were <hi>Circum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tanced,</hi> I am willing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lieve that theſe may not be to the <hi>Charitable</hi> and <hi>teachable, altogether un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cceptable.</hi> My <hi>Auditory, Subject, Occaſion</hi> being <hi>Military,</hi> and my Text <hi>Metaphorical,</hi> if my diſcourſe had not been in <hi>Terms</hi> and <hi>Language</hi> ſomewhat <hi>anſwerable,</hi> it had not been ſuitable. I conceive a man ſhould ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Meaſure</hi> of his <hi>Theam</hi> to out our his Language by, and make it up ſomething according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de of his <hi>Auditory,</hi> I do not mean ſo as to pleaſe <hi>mens Humours,</hi> but to ſuit their <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> provided alwayes he keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithin the <hi>Bounds</hi> of a <hi>Scripture mode</hi> and <hi>Cut. Edification</hi> was my End, and <hi>Familiar plainneſs</hi> one of the mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing thereto. If ſome things ſeem <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt</hi> and <hi>homely,</hi> yet I hope they are all <hi>the words of ſoberneſs,</hi> and may have t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir uſe, if <hi>ſoberly</hi> and <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> read and improved. Nor is ſuch manner of ſpeaking on like Occaſion without the <hi>Warrant</hi> of <hi>Scripture Example</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I End with two Requests, Firſt, that you will vouchſafe acceptance of this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation</hi> as a <hi>Token</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the Senſe I have on me of my <hi>Obligati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons</hi> to you for your <hi>favourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſtruction</hi> and <hi>kind Entertainment</hi> of my poor Labours already manifeſted by you: Next that you will joyn with me in ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Prayer to <hi>the Lord of Hoſts</hi> that he who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly can, would <hi>teach us all to profit,</hi> hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us ſo to run that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may obtein, ſo to fight, not as thoſe that beat the Air, but b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> down, and keep down ſin and the reſt of our Spiritual Enemies, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt while ſpeaking to others, hearing or reading what comes from others, any of us ſhould be caſt away. To his bleſſing <hi>I</hi> commend you and theſe Endeavours for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in your Spiritual Warfare Joſhua Moodey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100070:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 COR. 9. 26.</bibl>
               <q>So Fight I, not as one that beats the Air.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is commonly and not inconveniently ſaid, that a Mans general and particular Calling are the two Legs on which he Travels through the Wilderneſs of this World, from <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Canaan,</hi> he that fails in either of them will prove a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame Chriſtian, he may happily hop or creep, but will not be able to go uprightly, much leſs will he run the Race that is ſet before him ſo as to obtain. To uſe both theſe Leggs, and yet to ſet the beſt Legg foremoſt, I mean his <hi>General Calling,</hi> and to make the other, <hi>viz,</hi> that of his <hi>Particular</hi> ſubſervient to his <hi>General,</hi> is the <hi>Duty</hi> of every one that will be and appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to be a Chriſtian indeed. But ſo to do, we may ſay of it, <hi>this is a labour, this is a work.</hi> Oh how hard is it for theſe not to Interfere one upon another, and Interfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing how dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, how pernicious! A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the more, becauſe the <hi>General Calling,</hi> and ſo the <hi>One thing neceſſary</hi> uſually com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s by the worſt of it. <hi>The many things</hi> do ſo <hi>clamorouſly</hi> and <hi>cogently</hi> call for <hi>Attendance,</hi> and we are ſo ready to be at their Beck when they call, that it is many to one, if <hi>the one thing</hi> be not neglected and overlookt by means of <hi>the many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prevent this, beſides the <hi>Cautions, Counſels, Warnings, Commands, Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Threatnings</hi> that the Scripture is full of, to make us look to the <hi>main chance,</hi> to mind the great buſineſs that is before us: I ſay b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſides all theſe means, the Lord takes care to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſpiritual in all our Imployments, by ſpiritualizing all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Imployments. Yea, all our Relations and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as well as Imployments, are ſo improved to our Hands by the Spirit of God in his Word as that they may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> uſeful both as <hi>Monitors</hi> and <hi>Help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> to mind us of, and further us in thoſe matters that are of moſt ſolemn and mom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntous, becauſe of Eternal Concernment. Thus our hungring, thirſting, eating, drinking, ſleeping, wakeing, walking, ſitting, working, reſting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us the Relations of Huſband, Wiſe, Parents, Children, Maſters, Servants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are particularly mentioned a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull of precious a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d practical Inſtructions. Thus our Callings, Functions, or Occupations, whether more liberal or <hi>Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> each of them bears twins, and there is none barren among them The Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God is teaching us out of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proper V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cations are ſo many, ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, &amp; ſo pertinent, that they are enough to leave us without excuſe, if we are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100070:4"/> not ſpiritual in them, and learn not to be more ſpiritual whiles about them. To give a Taſt in a few Inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ces.</p>
            <p>The Phyſitian and Chirurgion when viſiting or adminiſtring to the ſick or lame, giving <hi>Purges, Cordials,</hi> &amp;c. ſetting bones, applying Plaiſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be minded of his own Condition by nature, convinced of his need of Chriſt, directed to apply himſelf to Him, as the <hi>great Phyſitian, Soul-Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who is <hi>anointed and appointed by the Father to bind up, heal, recover,</hi> yea, to do that which is out of the reach of all Phyſick, <hi>viz. to quicken the dead,</hi> Joh. 5. 25. ſee alſo <hi>Hoſ. 6. 1, 2. Pſal.</hi> 146. 8. and 147. 3. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 8. 22 Mal. 4. 2. Luk. 4. 18. Pſal.</hi> 51. 8.</p>
            <p>The Merchant is adviſed among all his dealing and trading in the world, to act the part of that wiſe Merchant, <hi>by ſelling all for the Pearl,</hi> which will be the beſt, and ſhould be the firſt bargain he makes, <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 45, 46. And he is aſſured by Chriſt <hi>the wiſdome of the Father,</hi> that he can deal in no Commodities that will yield him like Profit, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 11, 18, 21. but what ever elſe he may get, if he neglect this, will come to a bad market at laſt.</p>
            <p>The Factour that is imployed by others, having an eſtate of theirs to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage to whom he muſt give an Account; His very calling minds him of his Relation to God the <hi>High Poſſeſſor of Heaven and Earth,</hi> from whom he ha's thoſe daily Conſignments of Life, Health, Food, Raiment, Goſpel, and all the precious things thereof, of all which great Betruſtments he muſt one day give an Account to his Principal, and woe to him, if through his Sloth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs, or otherwiſe he diſenables himſelf from rendring to his Owner his Own with Advantage. Indeed we are all <hi>Stewards</hi> of the <hi>manifold Grace of God,</hi> (1 Pet. 4. 10.) And that Text, that awful Text ſhould lye down and riſe up with us, and keep upon our hearts all the day long, <hi>Luk. 16. 2. Give an Account of thy Stewardſhip, for thou maiest be no longer Steward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Huſbandman ſhould own God in that wiſdom he teaches him about his Calling, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28. 24, 29. and know that himſelf is <hi>Gods Huſbandry,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 9. and that therefore he ought to be ſo towards God as he expects his Land to be towards him after all the coſtly and expenſive Huſbandry that he hath been the Subject of, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5. 1-4. The dealing of Husbandmen is much in Earth, and leſt they ſhould loſe and bury up their Souls alive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſo miſs Heaven, God hath put a great deal of Heaven into their Earth and there they may find it, their fencing, clearing, plowing, ſowing, weeding, plucking up the thorns, waiting for the <hi>former and latter rain,</hi> reaping, gathering into the Barn, threſhing, winnowing, are all made in Scripture ſimilitudes, and ſo teachers of Heavenly things, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 3-9. and <hi>ver.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>-23. with <hi>ver. 24, 25. &amp;c.</hi> Math. 3. 10, 12</p>
            <p>The Fiſherman if he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will read, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th.</hi> 13. 47. may thence learn to catch <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Kingdome of Heaven</hi> in his Net, and ſome ſpiritual Good with his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100070:4"/> Hook and Line. And it is obſervable that in <hi>ver.</hi> 52. of that Chapter: he be ſpeaks his Diſciples as perſons well inſtructed unto the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> by means of thoſe ſimilitudes which out of their Secular Affairs and ordinary Imployments he had borrowed and ſuited to their Uſe.</p>
            <p>It would be endleſs to particularize, for even from the King upon the Throne to the Hewer of wood and drawer of water, the Lord is in his word teaching us by ſuch familiar and known <hi>Metaphors</hi> taken from thoſe Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings that we are verſed in, in ſo much that all ſorts of men may ſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the voice of God in his word, as they in another Caſe. <hi>Act.</hi> 2 8, 11. How is it that we hear from thence in our own Tongue wherein we were born, and in the proper <hi>dialect</hi> of thoſe Imployments to which we have been bred, the wonderful Counſels of God declared to us! the Lords manner of ſpeaking as it helps us to the underſtanding of what he ſaith, ſo his love and Care therein ſhould quicken us to the practiſe of what we underſtand. They that would ſee more of this may conſult theſe and ſuch like Scriptures, <hi>Joh. 15. 1, 2, 5, 7. Math.</hi> 9 16, 17. and 19. 24. <hi>Luk. 12: 19, 20, 21. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> 18. 1-4, &amp;c. <hi>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fer</hi> Rom. 9. 21 Pſal 2 9. Math. 7. 24, <hi>&amp;c:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to avoid any further ſkirmiſhing at a diſtance, and to come to a more cloſe Engagement with my Text, in which the Calling or Profeſſion of the Souldier is made uſe of as Inſtructive to the Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>My work this day principally is to attend a Call from, and ſo to ſpeak ſomething to Souldiers, and I knov no better way to ſpeak to their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings and Hearts then to ſpeak in their own <hi>Dialect,</hi> to treat them not only as Chriſtians but alſo as Souldiers, or as <hi>Chriſtian Souldiers.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my diſcourſe ſhall be a <hi>Divinity-Lecture</hi> to ſuch, <hi>i. e. Military-Divinity</hi> or <hi>Divine Souldiery,</hi> for the doing of which my Text advantageth me, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in it the great work of a Chriſtian in <hi>working out his Salvation,</hi> ſet forth under the <hi>Metaphor</hi> of <hi>fighting,</hi> and the manner of doing that, by the manner of doing this, [<hi>So fight I</hi>]</p>
            <p>I might give you the <hi>Coherence</hi> of the <hi>Text</hi> with the former part of the <hi>Chapter,</hi> and of that with the latter part of the foregoing <hi>Chapter,</hi> which for brevity ſake I omit.</p>
            <p>It may ſuffice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſay, that having exhorted them to <hi>run the Race that is ſet before then,</hi> and u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d his Exhortation from the Example of other <hi>Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>Strivers</hi> or <hi>Wrestlers,</hi> who were careful and intenſe in their way, though the Argument or Motive to urge them thereto were ſmall and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rable compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with theirs. The one being a <hi>Corruptible,</hi> the other an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ible Crown.</hi> He doth now in <hi>ver.</hi> 26. reinforce his Exhortation to them by the propoſal of his own Example before them, and that under a <hi>double Metaphor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>Of Running,</hi> concerning which he ſpeaks,</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100070:5"/>
            <p>1. Affirmatively, <hi>I ſo Run.</hi> 2. Negatively, <hi>not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uncertaint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing,</hi> which is before us in the words read, where the Apoſtle preſents himſelf in the <hi>Eq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ipage</hi> of a <hi>Souldier,</hi> whoſe Buſineſs is <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ting,</hi> amplified from the manner of his doing it, [<hi>So ſight</hi> I] and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ts down in the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tively, [<hi>not as one that beats the Air</hi>] In the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x. Affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mative<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, [<hi>I keep under my Body,</hi> &amp;c.] Together with the Reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the whole [<hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> while I pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach to oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt away.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So] i. e.</hi> So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e had before expreſt, lawfully, and ſo as to attain the end, and ſo as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t ſucceſs, the <hi>keeping of the Body under.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght I</hi>] <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k word here ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red [<hi>Fight I</hi>] is by the Latine <hi>pugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ago,</hi> which m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt properly notes to fight with the fiſt. <hi>Pugil</hi> from <hi>pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na;</hi> and that from <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the Fiſt, though we uſe <hi>pugna</hi> for any manner of Fighting, for a battel or Skirmiſh where Swords and other Weapons are uſed; and ſo <hi>Pugil</hi> is rendred a <hi>Champion</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng Fighter. [Fight I]</hi> then may be, I act the part of a <hi>Champion,</hi> Now a <hi>Champion</hi> is ſuppoſed to be not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldier,</hi> but one <hi>ſingul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rly qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minently accom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liſht</hi> for what he undert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, one that is both <hi>Strong</hi> and <hi>Skilful.</hi> Hence <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> was called the <hi>Philiſtines Champion;</hi> 1 Sam. 17 23, 51. So that to <hi>Fight</hi> lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Champion</hi> means to <hi>Fight</hi> like an <hi>able, Skilful, Active man,</hi> a man of whoſe <hi>Fighting</hi> well, there is <hi>Great Expectation,</hi> and upon whoſe ſo doing there is no <hi>ſmall dependance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not as one tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Air</hi>] A very <hi>ſignificant Expreſſion</hi> borrowed from thoſe that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke a Flouriſh with their Weapon, make a ſhew of doing much, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reas all they do is but a meer ſhew, an empty ſhow; they draw the Sword and wave it too and fro, but hit nothing beſides <hi>Air</hi> with it. This ſame Apoſtle hath a <hi>Parallel Expreſſion</hi> that will give ſome light to this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 9. He that ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks <hi>unintelligible</hi> wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds, he ſpeaks in the <hi>Air,</hi> i. e. he ſpeaks <hi>inſignificantly</hi> and <hi>unprofitably</hi> to his Hearers, whoſe Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may have the Sound, but themſelves not having the Senſe of what he ſpeaks, his words <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Air,</hi> i. e. are to no purpoſe. He makes a <hi>Great Sound</hi> with his high and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard words, but they are <hi>Airy,</hi> there is nothing in them to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs. So her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome mens Actions are as empty as other mens words, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a <hi>Flouriſh</hi> in the <hi>Air.</hi> This Phraſe may be anſwered by the Latin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which (beſides other ſignifications) meaneth only to <hi>Flouriſh.</hi> The Poet ſpeaking of one that was but a <hi>Flaſh, a Bubbie, a Vap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur,</hi> ſaith of him, he ſprea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s abroad his Arms indeed, makes a ſhew, pretends to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g, but <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erat ictibus A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ras,</hi> He ſtrikes nothing but Air with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lows. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o do, ſpeak big, and look high, make a very fair <hi>Flouriſh</hi> with thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Swords, wave their Weapons too and fro, carry them over their Heads, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d about them very neatly and dexterouſly, ſo that they appear very <hi>Skilful, able</hi> and <hi>valiant men,</hi> that can dare and do much; but this is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100070:5"/> only while there is nothing but Air before them, upon which they may ſtrike while they will without any danger of being ſtricken again, ſuch may paſs for fair Flouriſhers, but are no Fighters. It is not ſo with me (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) I have ſomething before me beſides Air, and therefore have other work to do then to beat <hi>That.</hi> I have an Enemy before me which I muſt ſtrike, and ſtrike down too, and that at my utmoſt peril.</p>
            <p>The Summe is, he commends to them by his own Example, Fighting for their work and Imployment, and by his Negation of <hi>beating the Air</hi> only, he implies and intends the Contrary Affirmative, <hi>viz.</hi> that he was thorough, intenſe and in good earneſt about his work, he did not make a ſhow only, then he did do the thing, there was not an outſide, an appearance only, then there was the ſubſtance, the reality, and as he did, they ought to do alſo. Hence take up this plain Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>To be in the Equipage or Capacity, and to perform the work of a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and that vigorouſly, ſtoutly, ſtrongly, ſtrenuouſly, is the Duty incumbent upon every Chriſtian.</hi> The Calling and Imployment of a Souldier is that alſo of a Chriſtian, in which he is to acqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf ſtrenuouſly and like a man. He that will be a Chriſtian indeed muſt be a Chriſtian Souldier and that in deed, in reality, not in ſhow or appearance, he muſt fight not flouriſh only, be a Souldier and that in actual Service too, [<hi>So Fight I</hi>] in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Tenſe, fighting is with every Chriſtian alwayes in the Preſent Tenſe. A Chriſtian muſt engage in a ſpiritual warfare, and therein he muſt not be like <hi>one that beats the Air.</hi> No, but he muſt act the part or do the work of a Souldier, and that in good earneſt. He muſt not be the picture of a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, a Fencer, a Stage player, one that comes on the Stage and for pleaſure, ſport or in jeſt only perſonates a Souldier, when he really is, and means no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs, but he muſt buckle to the Buſineſs of Fighting like a man that aims to make work of it. In a word, we need not alter the Terms of the Text. It is the Duty of every Chriſtian to look at and carry himſelf as a Souldier in the Fight, wherein he is to behave or demean himſelf not like <hi>one that beats the Air.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrine hath two parts in it, The one, the calling or Imployment of a Chriſtian, <hi>viz</hi> he is to Fight, the other contains the manner of his doing it, not flightily, but Subſtantially, not in jeſt, but in good earneſt.</p>
            <p>I ſhall draw forth each part by it ſelf, and ſpeak to each ſingly by way of Explication and Confirmation, and then make ſome Application of both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <div n="1" type="doctrine">
               <head>The firſt Part of the Doctrine.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Chriſtian muſt be a Souldier.</hi> That which I mean by it is that there is a great Harmony, Likeneſs, or Similitude between the work of a Souldier and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100070:6"/> that of a Chriſtian. The Art of Souldiery doth fitly reſemble the Art of Chriſtianity, and may be profitably improved to ſet forth the Nature thereof.</p>
               <p>That this is ſo, and wherein it is ſo, will appear if we Conſider,</p>
               <p>1. That the Spirit of God often puts the Name of Souldiers upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and be-ſpeaks them in. Terms borrowed from that Profeſſion: the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ints alſo have familiarly profeſſed or confeſſed themſelves to be ſuch. See 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 3, 4. and 4. 7. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 12. and 1. 18. So <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>Archip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus his fellow Souldier,</hi> Philem. 2. and that not only as a preacher of the Goſpel, but as a Chriſtian. Hence we commonly and Scripturally call the Church on Earth, the <hi>Church-Militant,</hi> i. e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>warring</hi> or <hi>warfaring-Church,</hi> the <hi>Army</hi> or <hi>fighting Company,</hi> So <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. 7, 8. and 6. 4, 10, 11. There are two parts of the Church of Chriſt, (anſwerable to the two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they are, or States wherein they are, <hi>Earth and Heaven, Grace and Glory</hi>) viz. that which is <hi>Militant,</hi> and that which is <hi>Triumphant,</hi> that which is yet warring, and that which is now in <hi>Triumph</hi> after the end of the Warr, wherein they have been <hi>Victorious,</hi> and their being <hi>Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant</hi> hereafter, ſpeaks them <hi>Militant</hi> now.</p>
               <p>2. The Qualifications or Indowments of Chriſtians are ſuch as are the <hi>Characteriſtical Notes</hi> or <hi>Badges</hi> of <hi>good Souldiers;</hi> the ſame Excellencies that ſpeak a Souldier, ſpiritualized make a Chriſtian too. Take thoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments which are requiſite in a Souldier, and he that ha's them (taken I mean in a ſpiritual Senſe) is a Chriſtian alſo. Counſel and ſtrength are for the war, whether Literal or Spiritual, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 36. 5. Skill, will, Strength, Activity, Valour, Courage, compleat a man for either Imployment. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to know his weapons, and skill to uſe them, pruden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in taking the right means and Seaſon, Strength to undergo what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and Courage and Confidence to face and grapple with Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, not to be ſcared with words and ſhow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or frighted with falſe Fire, are neceſſary Qualifications for Souldiers and Chriſtians, and for no Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier more then for a Chriſtian Souldier, and in no <hi>warfare</hi> more then the <hi>Spiritual.</hi> Courage in ſpecial is Eſſentially needful to both. The Time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, Cowardly or Fearful <hi>lead the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>an</hi> of them that are ſent to the <hi>Bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit,</hi> Rev 21. 8.</p>
               <p>3. If we lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k into their <hi>Accoutrements</hi> as well as <hi>Accompliſhm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances will further appear. A Believer fitted for Service and fixed for his Imployment, as ſuch, is like a Souldier in the Field compleatly armed <hi>Capape.</hi> You have the <hi>Christians Armory,</hi> Eph. 6 11-17. which ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proves his <hi>Souldiery. Truth is his girdle, Righteouſneſs his Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, Preparation of the Goſpel his Shooes, Hope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s Helmet, the Word his Sword,</hi> and now when theſe are on, he is fit to <hi>meet with Principalities and Powers</hi> (at leaſt when by Prayer, which follows in the next words, he hath engaged <hi>the Lord of Hoſts to be with him</hi>) What will you call one ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100070:6"/> 
                  <hi>equipped</hi> or <hi>accoutred</hi> but a <hi>Souldier,</hi> and what is he to expect but <hi>Fighting?</hi> He is not thus armed (ſure) either to play or ſleep. If God provides, ſends him and wills him to <hi>put on this Armor,</hi> you may readily conclude what Service he is to go upon. If the <hi>Lord of Hoſts arrays him thus with Truth, Righteouſneſs, preparation of the Goſpel of Peace, puts hope on his Head, Faith in the one Hand, and the word in the other,</hi> and bids him thus ſtand, yea, and withal bids him to call theſe his <hi>Belt, Breaſt-plate, Head-piece, Sword and Shield,</hi> no wiſe man but will account ſuch an one ſufficiently mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a <hi>warfare</hi> before him. God would never have called his <hi>Graces</hi> in the Believer and his word given to him, Arms and weapons, if his <hi>Calling</hi> had not been <hi>Military,</hi> and his work <hi>Fighting.</hi> If God bids men <hi>Arm,</hi> they may expect that the next word of <hi>Command</hi> will be <hi>Fall on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> or elſe they will be by the Enemy <hi>fallen on,</hi> and ſo they muſt look to <hi>fall down.</hi> And this makes way for the next particular.</p>
               <p>4. A Chriſtian muſt be a Souldier &amp; be in actual Service too, if we conſider the multitude of Enemies that are about him to keep him doing. When God hath given a Chriſtian his Armor, he will ſoon ſee thoſe that will neceſſitate him to put it on and uſe it too. No ſooner hath the Lord armed him, but the Enemy will alarm him, &amp; put <hi>his Armor to proof,</hi> whether it be <hi>Armor of Proof</hi> or no. He is no ſooner converted but be-ſet, Enemies ſurround him, aſſault him, ſo that he muſt either <hi>Fight</hi> or dye. The way to Heaven lies through the Enemies Country, and no getting through but by force of Arms. He muſt diſpute every ſtep at the <hi>Swords point.</hi> Heaven wuſt be won by the Sword e're i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be worn. Your <hi>Spiritual Enemies</hi> will do as they, <hi>Namb.</hi> 20. 21, 22. not ſuffer you to paſs through, but come out againſt you with a ſtrong hand, and you muſt not turn away from them but <hi>Fight</hi> them as, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21. 22, 24. The Lanes are filled, the Hedges lined with Enemies to impede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our March <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aan ward,</hi> ſo that you muſt engage againſt them, or ſhame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ully retreat and looſe all. Then, He that ha's but what he wins by the Sword, gets no farther then he <hi>Fights,</hi> and holds, and keeps no more then what he keeps by the ſame means which he gets it by, ſure this man is a <hi>Souldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> and ſuch a life is a <hi>Souldiers life;</hi> But ſuch is the Caſe of a Chriſtian. <hi>Ergò.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be endleſs to reckon up all his Enemies. Time would fail, ſhould we only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll over their Names and no more. But there be theſe four Heads which have thouſands under them, <hi>viz. Sin, Self, Satan, World.</hi> I aim not at accurateneſs of diſtinction, (for I know that <hi>Self</hi> is Sin) but at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> familiar plainneſs which may be <hi>Intelligible</hi> unto all, and they are common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſo diſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Sin,</hi> which is in and about, and <hi>doth ſo eaſily be ſet us,</hi> Heb. 12. 1. and muſt be fought by thoſe that will <hi>run the Race ſet before them,</hi> who muſt therefore <hi>Fight</hi> as well as <hi>Run.</hi> Sin I ſay, which on thy firſt coming to Chriſt thou muſt renounce, and wage warre with ever after. A warr and a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100070:7"/> bloudy warr too muſt be wag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d agaidſt Sin, <hi>Heb,</hi> 12. 4. You muſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Enemies to Sin, draw upon it where ever you meet it, keep it off at the <hi>Swords Point,</hi> ſtand upon your Guard, if it gets within you it kills you. Sin that <hi>deceitful thing that ſo often doth deceip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> under a Colour of being other then indeed it is. Sin that attends us in every Buſineſs, and lies in <hi>Ambuſh</hi> behind and in the midſt of all our lawful Imployments, and while we are buſy about them ſurprizes us at unawares. Sin that pretends in a friendly manner with <hi>Ioab to kiſs thee,</hi> 2 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 20. 9, 20. but ſuddenly and unexpectedly <hi>wounds thee fatally.</hi> Now with Sin thou muſt not compound or make a Truce, but <hi>Fight</hi> it at all Times, do not ſpare Sin at any Time, for it will ſpare thee at no Time. It will mix it ſelf with and miſchief thee in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Duty, Buſineſs, Imployment, when hearing, reading, praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Do not truſt it for it will deceive thee, and be againſt thee 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 29. 4. To be ever at variance and in actual conteſt with Sin is our work, and therefore this of a Chriſtian with Sin is rightly called, <hi>The Holy Warr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>Self,</hi> A cloſe Enemy becauſe within thee, and the more dangerous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo cloſe. <hi>Of ſinful ſelf,</hi> that ſaying holds true, <hi>where ſhall one find a worſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> friend then one brings from home?</hi> An Enemy that lurks in thine own boſome, and thence is advantaged to do thee the more Harm. They are bad Enemies that are of <hi>a mans own Houſe,</hi> worſe that are of <hi>his own Heart.</hi> Againſt theſe thou muſt be ever watching, or elſe wilt be fooled and foiled by them. There is in thee an <hi>old Man, a Body of Sin, an Army of Luſts that are ſtill warring againſt thy Soul,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 11. Thou needeſt not <hi>beat the Air</hi> for want of an Enemy to ſtrike. Thy Body thou muſt beet, yea, beat down, yea, <hi>keep down.</hi> There be <hi>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ong Castles</hi> and <hi>high Towers</hi> within thee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4, 5. that will never yield on Compoſition, but muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Storm. Thou haſt a <hi>Self</hi> that muſt be denied, ſubdued. A ſelf that mixes itſelf with all thy Duties, concerns it ſelf in all thy Buſineſſes, yea, with all thy Graces. (As there is pride with Humility, yea, pride of Humility) Thy <hi>ſinful ſelf</hi> muſt be mortified, and yet ſtill there remains a <hi>Righteous ſelf,</hi> (as ſome Divines call it) that will do thee as much miſchief as the other, <hi>Our own Righteouſneſs</hi> is as great an Enemy to us as our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs,</hi> our <hi>ſelf Righteouſneſs</hi> as dangerous as the other. <hi>Paul</hi> thought he had gained ſomething by his exact walking in the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of a <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee,</hi> having framed and ſtabliſhed a <hi>Righteouſneſs of his own,</hi> but he was fain to loſe all, deny that <hi>Self</hi> too, <hi>that he might w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſt,</hi> Phil. 3. 4. 9.</p>
               <p>A Chriſtian therefore muſt be a Souldier for he hath in him <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o contrary Principles,</hi> yea, <hi>two Armies</hi> engaged one againſt another, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 17,) lying one againſt another (as the Greek word imports like <hi>two Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> lying int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ched one againſt the other, or like an Army <hi>bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ring</hi> a City. There are <hi>fleſhly luſts,</hi> actings, ſtirrings on the one ſide; <hi>ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itual deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> tende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cies on the other, each ſide contending for its contrary Obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100070:7"/> and Ends. The Current of Natural Corruption ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s downward, that of <hi>Supernatural grace</hi> moves upward. Theſe two contrary ſtreams meet, and hence there muſt needs be an actual Conteſt; one draws backward, the other forward, hence there muſt needs be a <hi>perpetual Warr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. <hi>The Devil</hi> ha's a quarrel to thee, and <hi>Fight</hi> thee he will, and <hi>Fight</hi> him thou muſt. The firſt Cry of the <hi>New born Babe of Grace</hi> (ſaith a Divine) <hi>alarms all the Devils in Hell againſt him;</hi> what then ſhall he do if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>Fight?</hi> He muſt not fly, (unto God indeed he may fly, but from the Devil he may not, muſt not fly,) nor muſt he yield, then he muſt <hi>Fight,</hi> ſtand his <hi>Ground, reſiſt him ſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>faſtly in the Faith,</hi> and ſo make him fly, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 9, with <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 7. Thou maieſt and oughteſt <hi>lift up thine eyes to the hills from whence comes thine help,</hi> diſpatch Faith in Prayer for <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> from Heaven, but thou muſt <hi>Fight</hi> as well as <hi>pray, wrestle in prayer, pray and wreſtle,</hi> and that not with God only (as <hi>Gen.</hi> 32 24.) but with Satan too, <hi>Eph<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. 12. give no place to the Devil,</hi> the while, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 27. bate him not an Ace, <hi>veer</hi> him not an inch of ground, do not yield an hairs breadth, nor a minutes Time, we muſt ever watch and warr againſt him as our Adverſary, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 8. He follows thee from Bed to Board, from Company to thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements, from thy worldly occaſions to thy Cloſet, into thy Garden, Field, Ship, Shop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From thy houſe to Gods houſe, and there he ſtands at thy right hand. He is ever with thee, ſeeking Occaſions againſt thee. When he ſeems quiet, ſeems conquered, then perhaps moſt to be feared, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he retreats, goes forth, withdraws, but it it is for Advantage, that he may get ſtronger poſſeſſion with <hi>ſeven Spirits worſe then himſelf.</hi> It may be ſaid of him, as it was of <hi>Marcellus</hi> the <hi>Roman Commander,</hi> he was never quiet, <hi>nec Victor, nec Victus,</hi> neither beaten, nor beating, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vercome nor overcoming. In Converſion we run away from Satans Colours and Service, whoſe Slaves we natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ally are, and enter into Chriſts Pay, hence Satan purſues us (if poſſible) to regain us, and we have no other way to help our ſelves but by <hi>Fighting</hi> him. To be well acquainted with his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, Stratagems, devices, to watch him narrowly, and <hi>Fight</hi> him ſtoutly will be thy Intereſt.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>The World,</hi> one of the Devils Inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uments, that he uſes in the Warr, he is therefore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (in part at leaſt) called <hi>the God of this World,</hi> the world (I ſay) <hi>that ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aks the word,</hi> and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en undoes the Sinner. <hi>Beware of being intangled in the affairs of this life,</hi> if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u have t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n upon thee <hi>Chriſts Warfa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> 2 Tim. 4 4. Rather let thy <hi>Warfare</hi> eſpecially be againſt the world and thy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ared by it, He that while he lives in the world hath the world his <hi>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ant En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>my,</hi> he muſt nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſarily b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Souldie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Unto the world we muſt be w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d, and God oft <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s the Breaſts of worldly comforts, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies them up, yea, <hi>crucifies the world to us,</hi> makes it as it were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100070:8"/> dead to us, that we may the more <hi>facilely</hi> get Victory over it. The world <hi>Fights</hi> by preſenting preſent ſweet pleaſant things to allure to ſin and det<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s from obedience. Pleaſure, profit, Honour, are its baits to allure and draw to ſin or diſobedience, there be alſo many fears and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whereby it deters and drives bac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the way of obedience, Hence the World fires on both ſides; ſo muſt we alſo. Now look upon all theſe Enemies of our weal, theſe <hi>conſtant, perpetual, deadly Enemies,</hi> and ſay then if a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> can be other then a Souldier, and ſee if all theſe will not keep him ever in work. The <hi>New man</hi> hath the Spirit and the word that ſet in with him, and the <hi>Old man</hi> hath the Devil and the world to help him, each <hi>Party</hi> hath its <hi>Auxiliaries, Heaven, Earth</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> are engaged in this <hi>Warr,</hi> there is great ſiding and betting on either ſide, and there muſt be <hi>great Fighting</hi> by him that meaneth to win the Day.</p>
               <p>And hence what is the Scripture, but the <hi>Divine Art of Military-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> or the Art of <hi>Divine-Military-Diſcipline?</hi> where God is preſented <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Soveraign,</hi> Chriſt as <hi>General,</hi> all that will be Saints <hi>are his Followers, alias Souldiers, having given up themſelves to him,</hi> or liſted their Names under him, they are required to march and follow him in the <hi>Spiritual Warfare</hi> againſt thoſe forementioned Enemies, there are alſo directions how to <hi>Fight this good Fight,</hi> Encouragements to hearten them, threatenings to quicken them, Examples of thoſe whoſe valour ha's been crowned, and Cowardize puniſhed, the <hi>noteable Exploits</hi> that have been done by Believers <hi>by the strength and grace of their General,</hi> theſe and ſuch like things are the ſumme of the Scriptures. As in the ſecond and third Chapters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that which is driven at in the <hi>Epiſtles to the ſeven Churches of</hi> Aſia, and is the ſcopo of all the <hi>Directions, Counſels, Promiſes, Threatnings</hi> that are there ſet down, or diſcoveries of the Lords mind there made to them, is to make them good and ſo <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctorious Fighters,</hi> to put them on <hi>Fighting,</hi> and ſo as <hi>not to beat the Air,</hi> but to overcome their <hi>Spiritual Adverſaries,</hi> as appears by the <hi>Common Cloſe</hi> of each <hi>Epiſtle, [To him that overcometh]</hi> will I do ſo and ſo; why truly juſt ſo the very ſame is the ſcope of all the Scriptures to help us to <hi>Fight this good fight, and to finiſh our Courſe,</hi> that we may have the <hi>Crown</hi> at laſt.</p>
               <p>This alſo is the Lords aim in every Sermon we hear, to inſtruct us in the <hi>Theory,</hi> and ſo fit us for the <hi>Practice</hi> of what may ſpeak us ſuch as the Text and Doctrine ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of. Every Sabbath day is a <hi>Training day,</hi> wherein we receive Inſtructions and Directions from the Lord concerning our Duty, our work as Souldiers, and all the week after we are to act over the Leſſons which we then learn. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt our King, our General,</hi> knowing the multitude of Enemies within and about us, gives the ſame order which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did, 2 Sam. 1. 18, <hi>viz.</hi> that we ſhould be taught the uſe of the Bow, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100070:8"/> inſtructed how to uſe our <hi>Spiritual Armor Regularly</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsfully.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. The promiſed preſence and Aſſiſtance of God with his people in this world, in all their <hi>Buſineſſes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings, Exigents</hi> whatſoever, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in ſuch <hi>Metaphors</hi> as confirm the <hi>Aſſertion</hi> before us. <hi>He is with them,</hi> but how? <hi>as their Shield, Buckler, High-Tower, Fortreſs, ſtrong-Hold,</hi> &amp;c. All which with many ſuch like, intimate and inferr that they are in a <hi>Militant warfaring condition in this life,</hi> becauſe otherwiſe there would be no need of thoſe things. The Lord wanted not words to expreſs his Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his people by, but he uſes theſe as moſt <hi>ſignificant,</hi> becauſe moſt ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Condition, and ſo moſt <hi>Intelligible</hi> by them, and <hi>acceptable</hi> to them.</p>
               <p>Beſides, that the <hi>Reward</hi> at laſt is for <hi>Overcomers,</hi> a <hi>Crown</hi> to be put upon the Head of <hi>Overcomers,</hi> when they come into that <hi>Glorious Triumphant-ſtate</hi> whither the Lord is leading them, Now the <hi>great Triumph</hi> is at the end of the Warr (though Saints have ſome beginnings of it now, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14.) the <hi>Crown</hi> is for the <hi>Overcomers,</hi> the <hi>Overcomers</hi> are the <hi>Fighters</hi> or <hi>Souldiers;</hi> and therefore all Believers who ſhall be <hi>crowned</hi> muſt alſo <hi>Fight.</hi> All that are ſaved are <hi>crowned,</hi> all that are <hi>crowned</hi> do <hi>overcome,</hi> all that <hi>overcome</hi> muſt <hi>Fight, Ergó</hi> all the Saints that ſhall be ſaved muſt <hi>Fight.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="doctrine">
               <head>Second part of the Doctrine.</head>
               <p>That in this fighting they muſt be vigorous and in good earneſt, not like ſuch as <hi>beat the Air.</hi> Take this one Argument to confirm it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Becauſe no other acting but <hi>vigorous strenuous acting</hi> will attain the end, no other will ſerve the Turn, all other motions will be to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he that uſes them will be never the better, and as good never a whit, as never the better<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He that only <hi>beats the Air,</hi> will never beat his Enemy, and he that beats not his Enemy ſhall be beaten by him. None but he that <hi>Fights valiantly, couragiouſly, ſtrongly ſhall overcome,</hi> and none but he that <hi>overcomes</hi> ſhall be <hi>crowned.</hi> Sin and Satan will not be ſcared and frighted away (as was hinted) by ſquibs and Cracks, nor daunted with great words, nor made to fly with a meer flaſh in the Pan. <hi>Beating the Air</hi> will never beat the Devil <hi>the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce of the Air.</hi> No, you muſt run ſin thorow and thorow, your Sword up to the very <hi>Hilts, Ehud-like,</hi> prick it to the Heart, elſe it will not die; you muſt hit the <hi>Old-man</hi> under the fif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Rib and let his bowels out, elſe you do nothing. If thou deal gently with ſin it will be thy Maſter, but if thou wilt maſter it, do as <hi>Joab</hi> did by <hi>Abſalom</hi> who ran the darts through the very Heart of him. When you come to deal with ſin and Corruption, do your work ſubſtantially and throughly, <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t it fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to the Croſs of Chriſt</hi> that it may not have its liberty, elſe you'l never ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100070:9"/> your Comfort now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor your <hi>Crown</hi> hereafter.</p>
               <p>Many will ſometimes in a Fit talk of what they will do againſt ſin, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to leav it off, forſake it, kill it, give out that they will come out with ſuch a force againſt Sin, as that they make no doubt to ſtorm and take it; But Sin will give ſuch <hi>Braggadochio's</hi> leave to talk and vapour, and will give like Anſwer to them as <hi>Ahab</hi> to <hi>Benhadad,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>that the duſt of</hi> Samaria <hi>ſhould not ſuffice for handfuls,</hi> &amp;c. Let not him that puts on his <hi>Harneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> boaſt as he that puts it off, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20. 10, 11. Many will <hi>declaim</hi> much againſt Sin, while in the mean time they <hi>nouriſh</hi> and <hi>cocker</hi> it; but Sin cares not for words, values only <hi>blows,</hi> and <hi>down-right blows</hi> too. The Lord hates <hi>Cowards</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urſes d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eivers</hi> both in his worſhip, and other work and Service too, See, <hi>Mala.</hi> 1. 14. with <hi>Jer.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. <hi>Fighting</hi> weakly offends God, and advantages and encourages the Adverſary. <hi>Beelzebub</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>like the Flies medles not with fleſh that is boiling over the Fire, but when raw or cool will fly-blow and corrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it.</hi> The Application of it is Eaſy, if thou art <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rvent</hi> in Prayer, <hi>warm</hi> in Duty, <hi>vigorous</hi> in thy oppoſition of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> and <hi>Sin, Satan</hi> will avoid, <hi>Sin</hi> will yield, but if thou be <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>remiſs, Satan</hi> will grow more bold, and <hi>Sin</hi> more ſtrong. If thou art but a <hi>Fen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er,</hi> a <hi>Stage-Player</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> with a <hi>Button</hi> on the <hi>Point</hi> of thy <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pier, Satan</hi> will not be afraid to come near thee; but if he ſee that thy blood is warmed, and thy <hi>Spirits</hi> are up, and that thou offereſt the naked point to him, art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to <hi>Fight</hi> at <hi>Sharps,</hi> and layeſt about thee like a man, he will ſtand further of.</p>
               <p>When thou goeſt out againſt <hi>Sin thy great Enemy,</hi> perhaps thy <hi>deceitful Heart,</hi> that ſecretly too much <hi>loves Sin,</hi> will be ready enough to give ſuch a <hi>Charge</hi> as <hi>David</hi> did to the <hi>Captains,</hi> (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 5.) <hi>deal gently,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But Chriſt ſtands in the Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e as thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t going forth,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>for my ſake, and for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Souls ſake, and as ever thou wilt appear before me with joy</hi> at the End of the warr, <hi>deal ſeverely, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al ſharply and throughly with Sin and the Old-man.</hi> Thy <hi>Commiſſion</hi> is to <hi>take, kill, burn, ſink, deſtroy</hi> all ſin and Corruption, &amp;c. which are profeſſed Enemies to Chriſt Jeſus, and not to pity or ſpare any of them. It is like that ſometimes given to <hi>Saul</hi> againſt <hi>Agag,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 3. Then if thou ſpare any under what pretence whatſoever, thou wilt be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dighted,</hi> tried by a <hi>Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cil of Warr,</hi> found <hi>guilty, condemned,</hi> and <hi>executed</hi> for <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bellion, ſtubbornneſs, Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>raft</hi> and <hi>Idola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry.</hi> and ſo juſtly <hi>rejected</hi> or <hi>caſhie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſilly thing when the <hi>ſignal</hi> of Battel is given for men to charge with nothing but Powder, which will only make a ſound, give crack, but do no <hi>Execution,</hi> and yet ſuch Fools are many Profeſſors, they talk of Religion, talk againſt ſin, charge it highly, and diſcharge whole <hi>vollies</hi> of words againſt it, but there be no <hi>Bullets,</hi> they are not in earneſt, make a great
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100070:9"/> noiſe, aloud report, but the <hi>Report</hi> is all. They make a ſhew as Children do with their <hi>wooden Swords</hi> and <hi>Pot-guns,</hi> but they draw no bloud, no <hi>wounded luſt</hi> drops down, no <hi>bleeding Corruption</hi> lies gaſping for breath, or breathing its laſt, Sin is as ſtrong, luſt as haile, corruption is as ſound as ever it was, and ſo will be notwithſtanding their <hi>beating</hi> or <hi>breaking the Air</hi> with their empty words and unprofitable diſcourſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. Away with ſuch Childrens play, this <hi>play-Fighting, Fighting</hi> in <hi>Jeſt</hi> will never attain the end to make thee a <hi>Conquerour</hi> in earneſt; It may ſerve for a ſhow, and ſo Sin may be mortified in ſhow, and thou ſaved in ſhow, but damned in <hi>Real<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y.</hi> If thou let go ſin which God hath put into thy hand, without putting it to Death, (as he did him who was appointed to Death, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20. 42.) and if thou only <hi>beat the Air,</hi> not it, (be ſure it will go.) Thy life muſt go for its life.</p>
               <p>No acting but <hi>Strenuous acting</hi> will do againſt the <hi>Old man,</hi> thou muſt fall on him <hi>Couragiouſly, stoutly,</hi> the word in the <hi>Context</hi> ſignifies to <hi>box</hi> and <hi>thump manfully,</hi> to be about the Ears of him and beat him all black and blew. <hi>Beza</hi> on <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 5. Where the ſame word is uſed tells us that a <hi>Noun</hi> from this <hi>Verb</hi> ſignifies bruizes that are black and blew from the ſetling of the bloud there, and indeed it is as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 30. <hi>the blewneſs of the wound cleanſes evil,</hi> &amp;c. So muſt <hi>Sin</hi> and the <hi>Old man</hi> be Served, elſe nothing is done, <hi>beating the Air</hi> then in theſe matters will not avail.</p>
               <p>Thus the Doctrine hath been in ſome meaſure explained and proved; we ſhall now improve it in ſome few particulars.</p>
               <p>Is the Life of a <hi>Christian</hi> a <hi>Souldiers Life,</hi> and is he ſo to act as hath been ſaid? Then this informs us ſomething of the Nature of,</p>
               <p>1. The profeſſion and practice of Religion, that it is no ſuch <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſy, ſlighty, indifferent buſineſs</hi> as many Profeſſors make of it. Indeed to talk of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and make a <hi>Flouriſh</hi> is eaſy, to <hi>beat the Air</hi> is not difficult; to ſeem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious is <hi>facile,</hi> but to be Religious is hard and will be found ſo. He utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtakes the matter that dreams of taking his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe, and nouriſhing <hi>Sloth</hi> in a <hi>Chriſtian Life,</hi> that as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as he hath given up himſelf to Chriſt, that now his work is over; I tell thee no, the <hi>Warr</hi> now begins, now there are <hi>two Principles</hi> in thee, and thoſe in an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot diſpute at the <hi>Sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ras point,</hi> and there muſt be <hi>bloud-ſhed</hi> and <hi>loſs of Life</hi> on the one hand or the other, And ſure this is no <hi>Childrens play.</hi> God knows the Sloth and ſlightineſs of mans Heart naturally, and therefore meets with it by ſetting forth a <hi>Chriſtians Imployment</hi> under ſuch <hi>Metaphors</hi> as will allow of no <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es, Exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pli gratia,</hi> Math. 11. 12. <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven ſuffers violence, and they take it by, force,</hi> Sin makes a violent oppoſition againſt thy going to Heaven, and therefore thou muſt alſo make a <hi>violent Reſiſtance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> If Sin and Satan c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100070:10"/> it thou ſhalt never have poſſeſſion of Heaven given thee, however not a <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>quiet Poſſeſſion,</hi> and therefore thou muſt make a <hi>forcible Entry.</hi> Again, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 24. you hear of <hi>Striving,</hi> being in an <hi>Agony,</hi> like men that are a <hi>wreſtling,</hi> who tug and pull, and ſhake one another, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all Advantages to give each other the <hi>Foil</hi> or <hi>Fall. Paul</hi> uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the ſame word of himſelf, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>I have Fought,</hi> &amp;c. I have <hi>ſtriven</hi> that good <hi>ſtrift,</hi> have well acted the part of a <hi>Wreſtler. Striving</hi> implies action, <hi>Intenſineſs</hi> of Action, and that againſt a great deal of oppoſition. So [<hi>Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>] in the <hi>Context</hi> is uſed in the ſame Senſe, now <hi>Running</hi> is oppoſed to ſtanding ſtill, and alſo to moving ſlowly, it is a <hi>vigorous, lively motion.</hi> So 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5, 10. <hi>Giving all Diligence, Jude 3. Contending ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neſtly,</hi> Pſal. 63. 8. <hi>Following God, following him hard,</hi> and that with the <hi>Soul,</hi> Rom. 12. 11. <hi>Fervency of Spirit, warm</hi> and <hi>vigorous acting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I need not go from this <hi>Metaphor</hi> of the <hi>Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, Fighting</hi> is work, not play, <hi>hard work,</hi> (2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.) mens work, <hi>dangerous work.</hi> And let us about this Warr, Conſider that it is.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Near u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, yea, within us, not at a diſtance, two Men in every Chriſtian.</item>
                  <item>2. Between us, our ſelves and our ſelves are the parties concerned.</item>
                  <item>3. Politickly and powerfully managed on either hand, by the Parties and their Auxiliaries.</item>
                  <item>4. Mortal, not ſome ſmall blows, light ſcarrs, but Death on the one or the other ſide is the end of it.</item>
                  <item>5. Soul-Warr, the ſoul is warred againſt, <hi>1 Pet. 2. 11.</hi> and the Eternal Weal or Woe of the ſoul is the reſult of it.</item>
                  <item>6. Irreconcileable without Atonement.</item>
                  <item>7. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tant without Intermiſſion,</item>
                  <item>8. Perpetual without End, till death puts an End to the Combatants and combate both at once.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I ſay, Conſider theſe particulars, and then ſay when may a Chriſtian be <hi>Lazy</hi> or <hi>ſlothful?</hi> what leiſure-Time ſhall he find to gratify a ſluggiſh Spirit? where is there any room for ſlighty and <hi>ſuperficial Carriages</hi> in his work? At what time may he have a Licence to ſay to his Soul, <hi>Soul take thine Eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry,</hi> (at leaſt in that ſenſe as he did, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 19. and many ſtill do) when will it be lawful for him to lay down his Arms, put off his Sword, unbend his Bow? where will you find from God or from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the work any allowance or Countenance for that <hi>dul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſs ſleepineſs, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity</hi> and <hi>Indifferency</hi> that finds ſo much Countenance among men? And do not wonder to ſee in your <hi>Journy Heaven-ward</hi> the way beſt rewed with <hi>dead Cark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſes,</hi> and to ſee ſuch Troops of <hi>dastardly Cowards,</hi> and <hi>white livered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> faint bearted, milk ſopps</hi> upon their <hi>Retrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and when you come there do not wonder to ſee ſo few Profeſſors there, but rather that any ſhould ſo <hi>Fight</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100070:10"/> as to <hi>Overcome,</hi> that conſidering the oppoſition, any ſhould obtain.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Then it will be good prudence for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> that are looking Chriſt-ward to ſit down firſt and count the Coſt,</hi> Luk. 14. 25-33, Chriſts deals plainly with us and tells us what we muſt truſt too, let not us deceive our ſelves. <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es ſons</hi> were for a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> but Chriſt tells them of a <hi>Croſs, a Cup, a Baptiſm and a bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter one too,</hi> Math. 20. 22, 23. and ſo ſhould we tell our ſelves of the <hi>Warr</hi> as well as the <hi>Renard,</hi> of the <hi>way,</hi> as well as the <hi>End,</hi> not only of the Crown to be worn, but of the Sword, that by which it muſt be won before worn.</p>
               <p>Many when they hear of the Goſpel and <hi>word of Grace,</hi> they like the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>-n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ground</hi> (Math. 13.) <hi>Immediately receive it with Joy,</hi> perhaps are told of the Warr, but do not conſider of it, or if they do it is the <hi>Plunder</hi> and <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs</hi> that their mind is mainly on, hence when they meet with bloud and and wounds, repent of their choice, <hi>when Perſecution ariſes they are offended,</hi> and lay down their Profeſſion as haſtily as they took it up incon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>derately, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. 20, 21. Its good therefore for a Chriſtian <hi>to look before he leaps,</hi> leſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath advanced he draw back again, throw down his weapons, run away from his <hi>Colours,</hi> and make a <hi>ſhameful Retreat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord Jeſus looks back on all that are following him, and ſaith, I have a <hi>Crown</hi> for you, but you muſt <hi>Fight</hi> for it; a <hi>Kingdome</hi> for you, but you muſt <hi>take it by Force.</hi> What ever Chriſt propoſes to us we ſhould Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of. Now his queſtion to us is, (and ſhould be ours to our ſelves) Can we <hi>Fight?</hi> can we venture where Arrows and Bullets ſhe? can we Face an Army? can we <hi>endure Hardſhip as good Souldiers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſus Chriſt</hi> muſt do? Can we bid defiance to Sin, ſend a Challenge to our <hi>boſome lusts?</hi> can we be content to live a life of oppoſition to every Sin? We are naturally for Eaſe and quiet, would ſain live without Care and fear, meet with no croſs or trouble, ſwim down the Stream without any ſtop or check, not to have a ſtrong Tide to row againſt, or be forced to turn it up againſt a <hi>Trade-wind</hi> of <hi>perpetual Oppoſition.</hi> Moſt are like <hi>Iſſachar</hi> to whom reſt is ſweet, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 14. whereas we ſhould be like <hi>Judah,</hi> and divers other of the <hi>Tribes</hi> who are deſcribed to be of <hi>warlike Spirits,</hi> ſome with open force, others with <hi>ſubtle Stratagems</hi> engaging againſt their Adverſaries, Only that <hi>Tribe</hi> was <hi>dull</hi> and <hi>low-ſpirited.</hi> We are therefore to examine our own Hearts, God will try them and ſo ſhould we. The Lord would not lead <hi>Iſrael</hi> by that way leſt they ſhould ſee vvar and ſo recant, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. 17. but God will lead us that way where we ſhall ſee <hi>Warr,</hi> and that vvay we muſt go or none, for there is no other, and <hi>woe to us</hi> if we do recant.</p>
               <p>Great will be the <hi>Advantage</hi> that will ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue to us by <hi>due Conſideration</hi> of theſe things before hand, hereby we ſhall be put into a poſture of <hi>Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>difficultie,</hi> and <hi>hard Hardſhip</hi> in this <hi>Warfare</hi> will be no new thing to us, and ſo we ſhall not be ſo likely to be <hi>Surprized</hi> or <hi>offended.</hi> Expectation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100070:11"/> will put upon <hi>preparation,</hi> and that will be very <hi>profitable</hi> Chriſt told his <hi>Diſciple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> that his end in warning them of <hi>Perſecution</hi> before hand was to prevent their being <hi>offended when it came,</hi> (Joh. 16.-14.) Again, it will prevent our <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtatizing</hi> and <hi>falling back</hi> from our <hi>Profeſſion</hi> after we have engaged in it. <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from a Profeſſion mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ariſes from want of due pondering what we did when we firſt made it, and were like to ſuffer in the proſecuting of it. Therefore let us be adviſed and deliberate in taking up a Profeſſion of the Name of Chriſt, left that which was raſhly <hi>enterprized</hi> be <hi>groundleſly deſerted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. <hi>Let no poor ſincere hearted Follower of Chriſt be diſcouraged, as if all were not well with him becauſe he meets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith much Fighting and Oppoſition, no peace or quiet;</hi> Enemies come on him like the waves of the Sea, ſcarce can have one reſting day or night, <hi>the Devil</hi> ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r beating up his <hi>Quarters,</hi> his own <hi>Treacherous Heart</hi> often betraying him to <hi>Satans tempta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements,</hi> &amp;c. Why know this is no ſtrange thing, ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 12. <hi>Paul</hi> could tell you as much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all this upon his own Experience, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 7.) He ſtood to his Arms when he firſt engaged for Chriſt, and never laid them down till he came to lay down himſelf in the Grave. It was no Argument that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and his Company were not about Gods work, becauſe they were fain to hold the <hi>Sword</hi> in the one hand, and the <hi>Trowel</hi> in the other, <hi>Neh</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 17, <hi>Rebecca</hi> had no juſt cauſe of fear by reaſon of the <hi>ſtruglings and Fightings within her,</hi> Gen. 25. 22, 23. <hi>She had conceived by the Son of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> only there were <hi>Twins.</hi> Say not then, if ſo, why am I thus? Nay, if ſo, how can it be otherwiſe then thus? If a <hi>Believer,</hi> thou goeſt with <hi>Twins</hi> (the one the <hi>Oldman</hi> that is in thee naturally, the other the <hi>New, begotten in thee by Chriſt Jeſus)</hi> and theſe two muſt and will, yea, cannot but <hi>Fight</hi> and <hi>ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle,</hi> for they are contrary, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23. with <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 17. Thou maieſt bind the <hi>Old man</hi> indeed and keep him <hi>Priſoner</hi> that he ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un, but canſt never ſo bind him as that he cannot <hi>Struggle;</hi> He will Rebel while he has a Being, and while thou haſt a Being in this Life h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will have one too.</p>
               <p>To you that are diſcouraged bécauſe you feel the <hi>Body of Sin</hi> in you <hi>Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>disturbing</hi> you, let me ſay, there is one though you ſhould not feel it, and to feel it is a mercy, yea, to feel and <hi>Fight</hi> it is a Duty. That it is there is moſt certain, that you feel it there ſpeaks ſome Life, that you <hi>Fight</hi> it ſome Strength alſo, and conſequently your Frame is in ſome meaſure right, as well as your ſtate good.</p>
               <p>It is the Condition of every man to be either <hi>taken Captive</hi> or in <hi>Warr:</hi> if <hi>Captived at Satans will</hi> he may have a kind of peace for the preſent, but no wiſe man will think ſuch an one ſafe; if in <hi>Warr</hi> it ſpeaks thee gotten out, or at leaſt getting out of his Snare, and that is comfortable.</p>
               <p>Then let not Satan <hi>baffle</hi> thee, and make thee wound thy ſelf with thine
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100070:11"/> own weapons which thou ſhouldeſt uſe againſt him. Warr againſt Sin, if from a Principle of Life within thee, is a moſt certain Sign of a good Eſtate.</p>
               <p>Its true, there may be a kind of a <hi>Warr</hi> between a <hi>Natural inlightned Conſcience,</hi> and a <hi>carnal unrenewed Will;</hi> and between the <hi>ſenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Faculties</hi> in an unregenerate M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, but if the <hi>warr</hi> be between two <hi>Men</hi> in thee, be ſure one of them is the <hi>New Man:</hi> and if there be a <hi>new Man</hi> in thee, there is <hi>Chriſt</hi> in thee, and if <hi>Chriſt be in thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> thou ſhalt <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe other <hi>ſtrivings of Reaſon</hi> or of a <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>inlightned Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> are not againſt Sin as ſuch, and ſo not againſt all Sin, are uſually weak, nor do they grow more ſtrong, are <hi>inconſtant,</hi> and by <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi> only, not out of Hatred of Sin, but will conſiſt with a <hi>Trade</hi> of Sin, at leaſt with an <hi>Allowance</hi> of ſome <hi>ſecret-darling Sin.</hi> But if thou findeſt the warr againſt Sin as ſuch, all Sin, <hi>conſtant, growing,</hi> and ſuch as proves thee an utter Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to all Sin, ſo that thou canſt ſay thou wouldeſt never Sin more, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if ſo, thy <hi>Struglings</hi> ſhould rather encourage thee then otherwiſe. Do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an End of this <hi>Warr</hi> while thou liveſt, only live a Life of <hi>dependence on Chriſt,</hi> and from his <hi>death</hi> and <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſurrection</hi> daily, fetch <hi>ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wed ſtrength</hi> and <hi>Grace.</hi> What would poor <hi>combating Paul</hi> have done with his <hi>Body of Sin</hi> had it not been for Chriſt? <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>4. This Doctrine may alſo ſerve to give an <hi>Alarm</hi> to the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ure, quiet, eaſy Profeſſor,</hi> and that on a double Account, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>If thou be not engaged in this Spiritual Warfare.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>If though in a Senſe engaged, yet not Strenuouſly.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>1. Know, <hi>if thou art no Warrier, thou art no Chriſtian.</hi> If there be no <hi>Warr,</hi> there is no <hi>Grace,</hi> if thou know not what it is to be a <hi>Champion,</hi> then not what it is to be a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> neither. He that is no <hi>Souldier</hi> of Chriſt is no <hi>Servant</hi> of Chriſt. All <hi>Chriſts Followers</hi> have their <hi>Names</hi> in the <hi>Liſt</hi> of thoſe that <hi>Fight the Lords Batteli.</hi> He that now is, and ever was in peace, ſo continuing, now is and ever ſhall be without true peace. Do not cry peace, becauſe tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> never kneweſt <hi>Warr; Cujus Contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>m<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> He that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knows <hi>Warr</hi> ſhall never know <hi>Peace.</hi> He that will be <hi>cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned</hi> muſt <hi>Overcome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> he that will <hi>Overcome</hi> muſt <hi>Fight,</hi> then judge what will become of him that does not, cannot, will not <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght.</hi> You are either with Chriſt, or againſt him, <hi>Fighting</hi> for Chriſt or in <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to him, there is no <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> here, mind what was ſaid in the former uſe, if not in <hi>Warr</hi> then a <hi>Captive,</hi> oh do not bleſs thy ſelf becauſe thou art <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd at <hi>Eaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> are not <hi>in Trouble as other men,</hi> No, its a Sign that the <hi>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ong man A<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> hath <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> of thee, and therefore <hi>all is in peace,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inks it ſhould be a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng</hi> to thee to hear that thou art the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vils Captiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Slave, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l,</hi> as very one is that is not a <hi>Souldier</hi> of Chriſt. Thou that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt no <hi>warr</hi> with Sin majeſt be ſure thou haſt no Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with God I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100070:12"/> that when News came to <hi>Abraham</hi> that <hi>Lot</hi> was <hi>taken Captive,</hi> he and all his <hi>Company</hi> were up in <hi>Arms</hi> preſently: why let every <hi>ſecure Sinner</hi> know, every <hi>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iet ſinner</hi> that hath not yet <hi>given up his Name to Chriſt</hi> as a <hi>Souldier</hi> under him in this <hi>Holy Warr,</hi> I ſay let him know that the Lord hath ſent me to him this day, as his <hi>Meſſenger</hi> in his Name to bring him theſe heavy Tidings <hi>viz</hi> that nor his <hi>Friend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Acquaintance, Relation,</hi> &amp;c. but himſelf, &amp; that not his Body only, but his Soul, his <hi>precious, Immortal Soul,</hi> his <hi>darling,</hi> that is more worth in it ſelf, and ſhould be to him then <hi>Ten thouſand VVorlds,</hi> is <hi>taken Captive by Satan,</hi> and there vvithout <hi>Infinite Power</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> like to be a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Bondſlave.</hi> That <hi>roaring Lion thine Adverſary the Devil</hi> hath ſeized thee, thou art in the <hi>Dragons claws,</hi> and if thou beſtir not thy ſelf ſpeedily he will drag thee down into his <hi>Den,</hi> his <hi>Cave,</hi> the <hi>Bottomleſs pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> from whence no <hi>Ranſome</hi> ſhall ever fetch thee; No <hi>Ranſome</hi> but Chriſts now can, and when once <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay of Grace is over,</hi> which how ſoon it may be, God only can tell) that ſhall not neither. Oh is it poſſible for any <hi>ſecure Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ner</hi> to be ſo faſt aſleep as not to take this <hi>Alarm!</hi> God forbid. We account it a miſerable thing to be <hi>taken Captives</hi> by a <hi>cruel Adverſary,</hi> &amp; carried at a great diſtance from our homes and Relations into the <hi>Enemies Country,</hi> where we are like to waſt away our whole life Time in <hi>hard</hi> &amp; <hi>rigorous Service,</hi> in <hi>hunger, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hirſt, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs,</hi> and want of all things; and we think that all which hear of our Caſe are obliged to pity and pray for us, yea, &amp; (if there be need and hope) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omething toward our <hi>Ranſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> apply it then to thy <hi>Soul-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oncerns,</hi> &amp; think what it is to be in the <hi>Hands,</hi> and at the will of the Devil, the <hi>greateſt Tyrant</hi> that ever was, to Serve him with the <hi>greatest Rigour,</hi> in the <hi>hardeſt Service,</hi> for the <hi>longeſt duration,</hi> viz. that of <hi>Eternity,</hi> in the greateſt penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all things, no reſt night nor day, nor the <hi>leaſt drop of water to cool their tongues,</hi> and when thou haſt thought of this, ſay if it be not a Condition infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more miſerable then the other, and then again ſay, if it be not <hi>amazing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrange,</hi> that the ſame perſons that would be ſo much affected with the other, ſhould be ſolittle moved with this. Oh why doth not the world ring with the <hi>doleful Complaints</hi> of ſuch <hi>poor wretches?</hi> why do they not fill <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> with their Cries, and (being firſt alarm'd themſelves) alarm both to contribute to their Relief? Alas <hi>they know not that they are poor and miſerable,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>Rev.</hi> 3.) they feel not the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke</hi> upon their <hi>Neck,</hi> nor the <hi>Chains of darkneſs</hi> at their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls,</hi> at leaſt they do not feel Sin to be as a <hi>Yoke,</hi> as <hi>Chains, cords</hi> and <hi>Fetters,</hi> hence not <hi>ſtartled,</hi> not <hi>affected<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> but (<hi>miſerable ſelf-deſtroying ſinners</hi> that they be) ſtop their Ears at the <hi>Proclamation</hi> of the <hi>Year of Jubile, the acceptable Year of the Lord</hi> is not an <hi>accepted Year</hi> to them, they turn their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ks</hi> upon the <hi>tenders</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> hug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their <hi>chains,</hi> chuſe their Captivity, love their <hi>Bondage</hi> and refuſe to go out free. Hence though we ſee ſuch perſons daily, we hear any of them <hi>crying</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100070:12"/> and <hi>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oaning</hi> themſelves but ſeldom, hence in ſtead of following Chriſt who would lead them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of this <hi>Slavery</hi> they rather prepare Warr againſt him, and uſe their utmoſt Endeavours to keep themſelves in. Well, one of the next mercies to the giving of Jeſus Chriſt to a poor ſinner is the making him <hi>throughly ſenſible</hi> of his <hi>miſery,</hi> and <hi>diſquieting</hi> and <hi>diſtreſſing</hi> him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon withou Chriſt. Oh pray for that work to be wrought, and pray that none may (as it is frequent for many to do) look up a little at the firſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or reading of ſuch a Truth, but ſoon lay down their <hi>drowſy heads</hi> again, and make a Sui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ere long to get <hi>aſleep</hi> again, and dream that notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid, <hi>they ſhall hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>It alarms them that though they make a ſhow and pretend high, yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality do play rather then work, talk rather then Fight, and ſo indeed do but beat the Air.</hi> Chriſt loves to ſee a man that girds up the <hi>loins</hi> of his <hi>mind,</hi> and <hi>buck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> to his work, that puts his <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes</hi> as well as his <hi>Brains</hi> to it, and laies about him like a man. There's many that make a Shift to paſs among men for Chriſtians, who yet will want a place to hide their Heads in at that day when the <hi>Great General</hi> ſhall appear, becauſe they have been only perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Chriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>ſtage-players</hi> in Religion, that never yet had the Courage, or will, to Face any <hi>beloved ſin,</hi> or give it one <hi>ſound Blow.</hi> Thou haſt Flouriſhed thy Weapons about thine own head, but never gaveſt one <hi>down-right Blow</hi> upon Sins Head; this is not like Chriſt, nor will be liked by him; For when Chriſt is brought in as returning from the Fight againſt his Enemies, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63. 1, &amp;c. his <hi>Garments</hi> are all red with their <hi>Blood.</hi> It far better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Coat of a Chriſtian Souldier to ſee it ſprinkled with the <hi>Blood</hi> of Sin, then to ſee it ſpotted with the Fleſh, the former ſhould be laboured for as honourable, the latter hated as reproachful, <hi>Iude</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. which yet is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of every <hi>laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, eaſy Fighter.</hi> In ſtead of <hi>garments rouled in</hi> ſins <hi>bloud,</hi> they are rouled in Sins fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th and pollution.</p>
               <p>5. Be we all then Exhorted <hi>to ſtand to our Arms, Let us Fight, Fight the good Fight, and ſo Fight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fight</hi>] do not play, idle, ſleep when there is ſo much work to do, ſo many Enemies to oppoſe, woe to him that now ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with his Hands in his Pockets, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Arms folded one in another in the Slugg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ds poſture, as if there were nothing to do. Oh its a buſy world, and Fighting a buſy work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fight the good Fight</hi>] Fight for Chriſt againſt Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is the <hi>good Fight. And ſo Fight</hi>] not with their tongues, but Hands and Hearts, not with <hi>Flouriſhes</hi> but <hi>Realities,</hi> not with words but Actions; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Fight</hi> that you may <hi>Overcome,</hi> not ever Fighting and never Conquering<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ever learning and yet never underſtanding. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> often p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſing on ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Souls the neceſſity not only of doing b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> [<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> doing</hi>] without which all our doing is nothing worth and tends only to ſelf-undoing. Fight we muſt, and conquer we muſt, or elſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100070:13"/> it vvill be ill vvith us. We are in the ſame Caſe as thoſe Souldiers vvhom when the <hi>Commander</hi> had landed on the <hi>Enemies Country.</hi> he burnt up their Ships that tranſported them, and then told them that they muſt either eat up theſe men (<hi>i. e.</hi> their Enemies before them) or drink up that Sea, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating that there was no way left but to it they muſt, and that upon the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of their lives. God hath ſet us here in our <hi>Enemies Country</hi> where we muſt either <hi>Fight manfully,</hi> or <hi>die ſhamefully.</hi> Now to further us in this our work, take ſome <hi>Directions</hi> and <hi>Encouragements,</hi> and that,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Unto all thoſe who are or would be <hi>accounted Chriſtians,</hi> and therefore muſt be <hi>Souldiers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. To thoſe in particular, who are <hi>Souldiers</hi> and alſo <hi>Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> or to <hi>Chriſtian Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Souldier Christians.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>To the former let me ſay theſe following words, and that,</p>
               <p>1. By way of Direction, 1. <hi>Make ſure that your Names, and Hearts as well Names are given up to the Service of Chriſt.</hi> Remember that in your <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> you took <hi>Preſs-mony</hi> from the Lord, engaging you to ſerve him in the <hi>Warr,</hi> againſt <hi>the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil,</hi> and as you grow up he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects that you ſhould Anſwer for your ſelves, what ſide you are for. All men are Souldiers either in the <hi>Devils Regiment,</hi> or under Chriſts <hi>Banner.</hi> Be not then <hi>halting between two Opinions,</hi> be not <hi>Neuters,</hi> but <hi>deliberately</hi> make your choice. Jeſus Chriſt is lifted up as an <hi>Enſign</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and wherever the Goſpel is preached he ſets up his <hi>Standard,</hi> and cauſes it to be proclaimed by found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Trumpet,</hi> that whoever will fall off from Satan and come and put themſelves under him, they ſhall be welcome to him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by him. Oh then when he ſaith who wilt thou be for, ſay, let thy Soul ſay, Lord I will be for thee and for no other. He offers thee Conditions of <hi>Peace,</hi> comply with them then, for thou canſt not meet him in an <hi>Hoſtile way</hi> with thy <hi>poor, miſerable, naked Soul,</hi> who ha's his <hi>twenty Thouſand</hi> As <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. yea, <hi>Ten Thouſand Times Ten Thouſand</hi> to wait on him. Do not then <hi>harden thy heart against him,</hi> for <hi>thou wilt not Proſper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Then ſubmit to him, and be free in it. All Chriſts Souldiers are <hi>Volunteers,</hi> Pſal. 110. 3. They are the <hi>men of Deſires that offer themſelves willingly,</hi> Judg 5.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>That being done, enquire who are Chriſts Friends and Foes, and let them be thine too;</hi> do not miſtake and <hi>Fight</hi> Friends, while thou complieſt with Foes, and if thou doſt the former, thou wilt not ſhun the latter. Do not as they, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5. 20. hugg a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt when thou ſhouldeſt ſtab it, embrace a <hi>darling ſin</hi> when thou ſhouldeſt cut the throat of it, <hi>love the World</hi> when thou ſhould hate it. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra</hi> do not be ſhy of <hi>Holi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſs</hi> vvhen th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u oughteſt to <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck, purſue and perfect it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Be at peace with God,</hi> get and keep him on your ſide, and then none <hi>can be againſt you,</hi> at leuſt ſhall not hurt you, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Nothing vvill more <hi>further</hi> and <hi>ſucceed</hi> your Warr vvith Sin then your <hi>peace with God.</hi> When
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100070:13"/> 
                  <hi>Sauls</hi> Time of Puniſhment for his Treachery and Cowardize drew nigh, he buſtled all he could to ſave his Stakes, but God was departed from him, and then there was no help for him. Heaven would not, Hell could not relieve him though he implored Aid from both, ſee 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28, and <hi>Chap.</hi> 31. But if God be on your ſide, victory muſt needs be there too.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>Be Couragious,</hi> Courage is an <hi>high Accompliſhment</hi> of a <hi>Souldier,</hi> and moſt indiſpenſibly requiſite in a Chriſtian. Faint Hearts will ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves falſe ones, when the pinch comes. How often did the Lord ſay unto <hi>Joſhua,</hi> (Chap. 1.) <hi>Be ſtrong and of a good Courage,</hi> and it was on the ſame account that we are, when he was going to Warr for <hi>Canaan.</hi> Hear the Lord ſaying to us a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to them, <hi>Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 20. 1-4. and ſay we to our ſelves, and one another as they did, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 9.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>Get well armed.</hi> Good Armour will help to good Courage, he that is unarmed or ill armed muſt needs be faint-hearted, and one <hi>Coward</hi> is enough to ſpoyle a <hi>whole Company.</hi> The Lord hath a <hi>good Armoury</hi> where you may be furniſhed. See <hi>Eph. 6. 10, &amp;c.</hi> And when you have this Armour, prove it, try what your Faith can do, what your hope, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> can do. Suppoſe Caſes of Difficulty, as <hi>David</hi> does, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 1, 2, 3. and ſuppoſing your ſelves to be in ſuch Caſes, ſee what work you can make of it, ſuppoſe the loſs of friends, near Relations, Eſtate, Health, yea, ſuppoſe Death looking in at your window, try if you dare face it, make proof of the ſtrength of it, and ſee if you are able to grapple with it. Suppoſed Caſes will furniſh and fit you for real Caſes. Be often handling your Arms, and uſe will make you prompt, the frequent handling them will help you to handle them handily, expertly, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xterouſly, ſucceſsfully.</p>
               <p>6. <hi>Be at variance with every ſin, get inward, ſetled, radicated heart-Hatred againſt ſin as ſuch, and then thou wilt oppoſe every ſin.</hi> Correſpondence with one ſin will ruine thee. Do not ſpare any becauſe a little one (thy doing ſo will be a great one) neither dare to connive at any, becauſe ſometime a dear one, and ſtill a ſecret one. God ſees, and is a witneſs of all ſecret ſins, (<hi>Jer.</hi> 29. 23.) Be not bold, do not adventure to commit one ſin in hopes of a pardon, leſt <hi>the Lord of Hosts</hi> ſhould anſwer thee as ſometimes a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> did an offending Souldier who pleaded that it was the firſt Time, or he had done ſo but once, quoth he, Souldiers muſt offend but once. To ſin once is once too mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</p>
               <p>7. <hi>Begin with Sin betimes,</hi> ere it grows to an Head and the Conſpiracy ſtrengthen. <hi>Achitoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s Counſel</hi> was fatal if it had been followed. I will pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue him this night, while weak and weary, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 1, 2. Let this Counſel be acceptable to thee, it is (as was ſaid of his) as if thou ſhouldeſt ask Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel at the <hi>Oracle of God,</hi> nay it is the <hi>Oracle of God,</hi> follow Sin this night, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve againſt it this moment, and purſue it ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dily. Sin is like Fire in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100070:14"/> Houſe-Top, either quench it preſently, or elſe all will be in a Flame within a few moments, and in <hi>aſhes</hi> within a few more. The <hi>Twig</hi> will come up eaſily, but the <hi>Tree</hi> when grown up will be <hi>Inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncible.</hi> Sin is a <hi>great Breeder,</hi> a <hi>little Company</hi> will ſoon increaſe to a <hi>potent Army.</hi> And it will grow <hi>ſtrong</hi> as faſt as <hi>numerous.</hi> Then <hi>take the little Foxes,</hi> (Cant 2, 15.) the <hi>old ones</hi> may be too <hi>ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le</hi> and too <hi>nimble</hi> to be taken Begin with Sin as ſoon as it begins with thee, nip it in the <hi>bud,</hi> cruſh it in the <hi>Egg,</hi> the firſt <hi>riſings &amp; motions</hi> of Sin do thou riſe up in Arms and move againſt. The <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of <hi>Achitophels Counſel</hi> lay in the <hi>Circumſtance</hi> of <hi>Time [this Night]</hi> and hence <hi>Huſhai's policy</hi> was only to ſtrike at that, and by ſo doing <hi>enervated</hi> and weakened the whole, ſo that it was <hi>turned to folly.</hi> The <hi>Conſcience</hi> of many a ſinner is ſo far convinced of that <hi>plain Truth</hi> that ſin muſt be <hi>fought,</hi> that the Devil ſeeth it <hi>bootleſs</hi> to beat him out of that, dares not ſay the Counſel is not Good, only it is not good at this Time, what needeſt make ſo much haſt as to go this night, ſtay and ſleep upon it, <hi>to Morrow is a new day,</hi> another Time may do as well, and thus while the ſinner delays, <hi>Sin</hi> increaſes, delaying to oppoſe ſin is a ſin, and gives way to more ſin, and the renewing of the <hi>Act</hi> ſtrengthens the <hi>Habit. Cuſtome</hi> in <hi>Sin</hi> will prove a <hi>ſecond Nature,</hi> and be as <hi>incureable</hi> as the <hi>Ethiopians Colour</hi> or the <hi>Leopards Spots.</hi> Unto none is it of ſo great Concernment to take the very <hi>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> as <hi>Souldiers,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtian Souldiers.</hi> The <hi>Bratts</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> may more eaſily be <hi>daſht againſt the Stones,</hi> if we take the <hi>Seaſon</hi> for it, but if we let them grow up they will become more <hi>for midable,</hi> and <hi>hardly Conquerable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>8. <hi>Iu ſtead of making any Proviſion for, endeavour to cut off all Proviſion from the Fleſh, watch againſt the occaſions of Sin, and reſist them strongly.</hi> It's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>good Policy</hi> in <hi>Warr</hi> to leave as little Proviſion as may be in the <hi>Enemies way,</hi> men will burn and deſtroy even in their own Country to prevent the Enemies finding relief. How fooliſhly do they act then who pretend to <hi>Fight Sin,</hi> and yet ſecretly ſupply it with <hi>Proviſion &amp; Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to carry on the <hi>Warr?</hi> The <hi>Fleſh</hi> hath many In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entions to provide for it ſelf, will <hi>ſhift noteably,</hi> and <hi>the Devil</hi> is a <hi>careful Cater</hi> and <hi>Purveyor</hi> for it, it needs none of our help. He that keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not himſelf from the Occaſion, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect that God will keep him from the Sin. Some Luſts like ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſtrong-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olds</hi> may be eaſier ſtarved then taken by <hi>Storm,</hi> yea, no luſt will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e taken that is not <hi>ſtarved,</hi> or dye if you give it meat.</p>
               <p>9. <hi>Plant your main B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tery againſt your neareſt and deareſt Sins, your ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> iniquities. Deal with that Sin that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as a right hand, and eye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l moſt ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly there.</hi> Thoſe that thou art moſt endangered by, thou ſhouldeſt make moſt <hi>Oppoſition</hi> againſt. <hi>If</hi> there be any thing that holds <hi>Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſpondenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with the Enemy, no wonder thou art betrayed. Satan could do Chriſt no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rm, becauſe <hi>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ound nothing in him,</hi> Joh. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 30. The leſs thou haſt in thee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100070:14"/> for Satan, the leſs can he do without thee againſt thy ſelf. And indeed it is little that he doth againſt thee without thee, I mean, without thine own ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an Hand in it; the moſt he does is to <hi>ſtrike Sparks</hi> upon our <hi>Tinder</hi> or <hi>Powaer,</hi> to bring <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Bellows</hi> to our <hi>dry Stubble,</hi> do but damp that <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible matter</hi> that is in thee, and he will loſe much of his labour. <hi>Fight neither with ſmall nor great but with the King,</hi> was a Charge he gave his <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,</hi> (2 King. 18. 30.) So let us <hi>Fight</hi> mainly againſt the <hi>King-luſts, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Inclinations</hi> and <hi>Deſires.</hi> When the Enemies and Traytors with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are conquered, executed, at leaſt the <hi>Leaders</hi> or <hi>Heads</hi> of them, thou wilt with leſs danger oppoſe the Reſt. Let the <hi>Head-ſins</hi> be taken off, and the other will fly like the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> when <hi>Goliath</hi> their <hi>Champion</hi> was dead.</p>
               <p>10. <hi>When Sin begins to fall follow it cloſe, give it no breathing, no recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Time, purſue thy victery, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it not have leiſure to rally, but follow the Chaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> till none be left remaining.</hi> The <hi>Sun ſhall stand ſtill at</hi> Joſhua's <hi>prayer</hi> to give him opportunity to be avenged on his Enemies, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. 12, 13. If thou haſt a Spirit to pray and purſue Sin thou ſhalt want neither light nor help to give it an utter overthrow.</p>
               <p>11. <hi>Be much for Order.</hi> Chriſtians are Souldiers and that in <hi>actual Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe,</hi> now <hi>Souldiers</hi> in <hi>Exerciſe,</hi> at leaſt if they exerciſe well are great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers of <hi>Order.</hi> What is an Army in a <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut,</hi> or <hi>Christians</hi> out of their places? It was both <hi>ſightly</hi> and <hi>ſafe</hi> for <hi>Iſrael</hi> that came <hi>harneſſed</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to march in ſuch exact Order th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ugh the wilderneſs. Hear his ſaying concerning them, <hi>Numb. 24. 5. Order is B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y and ſafety.</hi> Then let each know and keep his own place, and not while inquiſitive into other mens places and duties, neglect his own. Let <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aders</hi> lead, and let the reſt follow; let <hi>Commanders</hi> command, and let the reſt obey, elſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e will be <hi>Confuſion.</hi> They are the beſt <hi>Souldiers</hi> that can keep from a <hi>Rout,</hi> and the next beſt that can <hi>rally</hi> ſooneſt. The beſt will ſometimes miſs it, but miſerable are they who when out cannot bear to be reduced or brought in. As much as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble keep in; if out, as ſoon as poſſible fall in again. Keep in your places and you keep out of danger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Strayers</hi> from their <hi>Colours</hi> or <hi>ſtraglers</hi> from their places will ſoon be ſnapt up.</p>
               <p>12 <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conſtant in Christs Service. His ſtandard is ever in the Field, do not fly from your Colours.</hi> The work of Chriſtian Souldiers is not a <hi>Rattel</hi> but a <hi>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> when once liſted never freed, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t after ſixty years, as in <hi>Iſrails Camp.</hi> Bewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of neglecting any Seaſon of going to <hi>Warr,</hi> 2 Sam. 11. 1.</p>
               <p>You read that <hi>David</hi> had a <hi>Battel,</hi> and yet again a <hi>Battel,</hi> and yet again a <hi>Battel,</hi> 2 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m 21 15, 18, 19, 20. No diſcharge in this war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> till death comes, and he is you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>my,</hi> 1 Cor. 15 26. you muſt <hi>Fight</hi> till you die upon the place. Reſolve to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and die <hi>Fighting,</hi> and then you ſhall live and die <hi>Conquering,</hi> yea, <hi>you ſhall be more then Conquerours,</hi> Rom. 8. 37.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100070:15"/>
               <p>Then loſe no Time. <hi>Alexander</hi> being askt, <hi>how he did ſo much, conquered ſo many places in ſo little time,</hi> Anſwered, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting no opportunity. We have many Enemies to conquer, and much work to do in a little Time, we had need loſe none, but by <hi>redeeming it</hi> to make more. Chriſt bade them <hi>gather up the Fragments,</hi> (Joh. 6.) which proved more then the whole that they had at firſt. Sure our <hi>Time</hi> is as <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> as our <hi>Bread,</hi> we ſhould then preſerve and improve every <hi>Inch, bit</hi> and <hi>Crum</hi> of it, let none be loſt; do not <hi>whittle</hi> out our <hi>precious Time</hi> into <hi>chips,</hi> break it in pieces, crumble it into bits; ſhould we gather up thoſe <hi>Fragments</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt in <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in chatt, needleſs Recreations,</hi> &amp;c, perhapsit would be more then the whole that many of us have ever made good uſe of to this day.</p>
               <p>13. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite firmly, ſtrongly and cloſely together. Chriſtian-fellow Souldiers you are Members of one Body, yea, members one of another, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n be one, and of one Heart at leaſt though you be not always in all things of one mind.</hi> It was the <hi>Devile maxime of old,</hi> and <hi>Machiavels</hi> ſince, <hi>divide and Conquer.</hi> It was <hi>Chriſts mind of Old,</hi> and <hi>his Apostles</hi> ſince. <hi>Be of one mind, live in love and peace,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Cor. 13, 11. <hi>Peaceableneſs</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> are <hi>Good Qualifications</hi> in Souldiers, and ſo in <hi>Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Gentleneſs</hi> in Souldiers makes them <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen Souldiers.</hi> All Chriſts Souldiers are of <hi>peaceable, me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k, gentle, quiet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>actable diſpoſitions. Innocent alſo as Doves,</hi> (Math. 10. 16.) <hi>do violence to no man</hi> ſaith <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> to the Souldier, (<hi>Luk.</hi> 3. 14.) <hi>be ſpotleſs, harmleſs, and without rebuke (yea, among a crooked and perverſe Generation</hi> that will provoke) ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to the Chriſtian, <hi>Ph.</hi> 2. 15. Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Souldiers <hi>ride on white Horſes, clothed in white Linnen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Rev. 19. 14. <hi>viz. Holineſs, Righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>couſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Equity, Innocence;</hi> to have an hand in any of thoſe <hi>dirty Actions</hi> of <hi>injuring, wronging,</hi> or <hi>quarrelling</hi> with any of your <hi>fellow-Souldiers</hi> or others, will be a ſpot ſoon ſeen on, and a ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſh to your <hi>white Coat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But eſpecially Cover her Characters of her ſelf, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 19. I am one that is <hi>Faithful</hi> and <hi>peaceable</hi> in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The Lord is a <hi>man of Warr, Ex.</hi> 15. 3. yet the <hi>God of peace,</hi> Heb. 13. 20. Chriſt is the <hi>Captain of the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Host,</hi> yet the <hi>Prince of peace,</hi> Joſh 5. 14 with <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9. 6. The Spirit maintains the Warr with ſin and Satan, and yet one of his main <hi>fruits is peace,</hi> Gal, 5. 22. while at Warr with all Gods Enemies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> at pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with all his Friends, and as much as poſſibly in you lies <hi>with all men.</hi> Saints have the moſt warlike, and yet the moſt <hi>peaceable Spirits</hi> of any men in the world. Their <hi>wiſdome is from above, and that is firſt pure, then peaceable.</hi> Let there be no <hi>Faction,</hi> or <hi>Fraction</hi> among us. If <hi>one Body,</hi> dread that there ſhouldbe a Schiſm in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Let not Chriſtian Souldiers delight to keep at a <hi>double,</hi> (perhaps it is too often <hi>double double</hi>) diſtance. If we are <hi>quarrelling one with another</hi> when we ſhould be joyning ſhoulder to ſhoulder to oppoſe the <hi>common Enemy,</hi> we ſhall make matter of ſport for our Adverſaries and ſhame and miſery for our
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100070:15"/> ſelves. And when our Captain comes to look on us, if he find us <hi>quarrelling and Fighting one with another,</hi> we may expect that he will frown, yea, and <hi>Fight</hi> too, beat us, puniſh us altogether. It is uſually obſerved that in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies and Contentions, though one party might be mainly to blame at the beginning of them, yet if they continue long, it is much if either be wholly Innocent.</p>
               <p>Our being Souldiers ſaith we muſt <hi>Fight,</hi> but our Rule as Chriſtians tells us againſt whom we muſt <hi>Fight</hi> viz. ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and for whom <hi>viz.</hi> for Chriſt and the <hi>Common Faith,</hi> not one againſt another, nor for ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Luſts, and yet from them all our <hi>Warrs</hi> and <hi>Fightings come,</hi> Jam. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1, Small matters oft make <hi>Great Breaches,</hi> A<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> little Earth ſometimes, <hi>a Fancy, a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mour, a Luſt,</hi> &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> why better loſe much of our Earth, Fancy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all our ill humours and Luſts then any of our peace. The <hi>Fig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 9. 11. feared loſing its ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs if it ſhould accept of promotion over the Trees: I am ſure while we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for promotion over others, contend to promote our wills and humours above others (and the Text tells us <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 10. that <hi>only by pride comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi>) we loſe our peace, our quietneſs, our ſweetneſs, and ſowre our ſelves, into a frame unpleaſing to God and unprofitable to our ſelves and others, and the Gain will never countervaile the Damage. One of the <hi>higheſt pieces</hi> of Souldiery is for a man to <hi>Overcome himſelf,</hi> and he that hath attained that skill will be a Conquerour where ever he comes, no evil ſhall overcome him, but he will overcome it by doing of good, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 21.) and that is the <hi>noblest conqueſt</hi> in the world. Miſtake not Courage &amp; valour to think it conſiſts in <hi>rendring evil for evil,</hi> (no, when thou doſt ſo thou art overcome, and ſheweſt thy ſelf a Coward) or being able to give perſons as good as they bring, to be even with them, ſtand out ſtifly againſt them and not yield, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No, he is truly Couragious &amp; ſtout hearted that can ſtoop rather then quarrel, yield rather then ſin. <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhewed as much true <hi>Chriſtian magnanimity</hi> when he yielded to <hi>Lot</hi> to prevent ſtrife (<hi>Gen.</hi> 13.) As when he faced all thoſe Kings and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Lot,</hi> Gen. 14. <hi>True magnanimity</hi> ſhews it ſelf in an <hi>utter Impotency</hi> and <hi>inability</hi> to do any thing againſt Truth and peace. Courage of the right ſtamp appears in daring to grapple and Collar with thine own Luſts and Corruptions, in <hi>enduring hardneſs,</hi> (2. Tim. 2, 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) and hard dealing too, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being put out of thy way thereby.</p>
               <p>Then let all Chriſtians <hi>move, act, harmonize</hi> as <hi>one Body; and members of the ſame Body.</hi> Refer our zeal and heat for the Enemy, and then lay it out when it may <hi>praiſe God,</hi> and be ſure the wrath of Profeſſors of Religion one againſt another does not work his <hi>praiſe,</hi> but <hi>diſhonour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martial Diſcipline</hi> is ſevere, and very ſevere againſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Woe to thoſe that begin, wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to thoſe that <hi>maintain,</hi> woe to thoſe that (as God gives opportunity) come not with their <hi>Pails</hi> of <hi>water</hi> to help to put out the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100070:16"/> 
                  <hi>Fire of Contention.</hi> God is angry at our being angry with one another, our ſelves are wofully diſtempered and damnified, others <hi>Scandalized</hi> and <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened,</hi> Satan only ſmiles becauſe he gains the while. In theſe <hi>pudled waters</hi> the Devil accounts (becauſe by experience he finds) that it is <hi>good Fiſhing,</hi> and though he cannot Fiſh out (no more then he could <hi>winnow</hi> out, Luk. 22. 31, 32,) any <hi>true Grace,</hi> yet he may deprive us of the <hi>preſent, profitable,</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Exerciſe</hi> of it; and he may, and often doth at ſuch Times fiſh out all the <hi>ſeeming grace</hi> of an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> and make him manifeſt in his own <hi>Colours. Quarrelling Times</hi> are <hi>trying Times,</hi> and <hi>manifeſting Times,</hi> thoſe that have any <hi>Faith, love, patience,</hi> &amp;c. it will then appear; and thoſe that had nothing but a <hi>ſhow</hi> of theſe will then ſhow what they had. Yea, the Saints themſelves when troubled, ſhaken and diſturbed by the <hi>Storm</hi> of <hi>Contention,</hi> do cauſe more <hi>filth</hi> and <hi>froth</hi> to riſe then either themſelves or others thought to have been there.</p>
               <p>Offences have been and will be, <hi>Controverſies</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> have been by Satan <hi>raiſed</hi> and <hi>fomented</hi> in all <hi>Ages,</hi> which have occaſioned great <hi>digladiations</hi> among Chriſtians. Hence <hi>Pulpits</hi> and <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſes</hi> have been more then glutted with many <hi>Polemick</hi> and <hi>unedifying Diſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes,</hi> beſides <hi>ſharp Debates</hi> in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, by which much precious Time hath been waſted, that will be dearly miſſed one day. And for men either in publick or private Capacity to be much (much more to delight to be much, and being much will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed delight) in thoſe matters, to travel farr in that <hi>Road,</hi> how well it ſuits with their feet who are to be <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>od with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace,</hi> (one piece of our <hi>Spiritual Armor</hi>) I leave them to Judge who have for any conſiderable Time worn that Shooe. To ſtudy to diſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et Luſt and ſin in our ſelves firſt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in others is given us in Charge, but in the mean Time to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet</hi> in our ſelves and with others, lies very fair and full in our <hi>Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions,</hi> 1 Theſ 4 11. with 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 12. That the <hi>Sword</hi> ſhould devour for ever while there is any Sin remaining to be the <hi>Antagonist,</hi> muſt be for ever owned; but if the <hi>Sword</hi> devour at all, much more for ever, while our Brethren are the Subjects of it, <hi>this will be bitterneſs in the latter end,</hi> 2 Sam. 2. 26 Let <hi>Pulpits</hi> ring with the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> the bitterneſs and vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sin, the excellency of Chriſt, the <hi>freeneſs of Grace,</hi> the neceſſity of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> toward God, <hi>Superlative Love</hi> to Chriſt and to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as our ſelves; and let private diſcourſes and <hi>Occaſional Conferences</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Fellow-Souldiers</hi> throughout the whole Army, be the <hi>Eccho</hi> of ſuch Counſels, and our Carriage and Converſation toward God and one another, the Examples of thoſe Rules, if (I ſay) men were thus buſied they would have little li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t or leiſure to quarrel, and many of our endleſs and <hi>fruit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies</hi> would die alone. There is a great deal o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſuality, worldly, mindedneſs, prid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Love,</hi> &amp;c. againſt theſe let the <hi>voice be lifted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100070:16"/> up like a Trumpet,</hi> and when men write againſt theſe, they may be allowed ſome <hi>Gall</hi> and <hi>Vineger</hi> in their Ink, only let us ſpare our Brethren.</p>
               <p>14. <hi>Walk humbly both with God and among men.</hi> If Humility be not one of the pieces of our Spiritual Armor expreſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. yet it is the Grace of the whole. Humility in a Souldier ſets him forth more then all his Bravery beſides; ſo Humility in a Chriſtian is the very Bravery of a Chriſtian. Its called his raiment, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 5. And indeed the reſt of our Graces are ſo ragged that we had need have the <hi>upper Garment</hi> of <hi>Humility</hi> over all, leſt <hi>the ſhame of our nakedneſs appear. Vain-Glory,</hi> which is the proud mans ſtudy, is an empty ſtudy, a vain ſtudy. Do not talk great words: nor make great ſhows or Flouriſhes, but do great things. Neither ſhould the Souldier or Chriſtian be a <hi>Vapour,</hi> a <hi>Flaſh,</hi> a <hi>Bubble, Von pretere à nihil,</hi> but be a through and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial doer in all that he does do, and let thy deeds ſpeak, and they will ſay enough, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. ult. Do high and loud d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eds: while you ſpeak little and low words, ſay little, but do the more, do not ſpeak <hi>ſwelling words,</hi> but do <hi>ſwelling works,</hi> and theſe works will ſpeak words big enough to guard thee againſt obſcurity or oblivion, will get thee a Name and Fame that ſhall never be forgotten.</p>
               <p>15. <hi>Know your ſtrength lies more in, and your ſucceſs is more from the General then your ſelves.</hi> The Security of our Lives is more from the Grace in Chriſt for us, then from the Grace from Chriſt in us. Indeed we muſt keep our Graces bright and in Exerciſe, our weapons on and in uſe, let not our Swords ruſt in our Scabbards that they will not draw, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet ſtill the Exerciſe of our Graces when we have them, and their ſucceſs when we uſe them is from him <hi>without whom we can do nothing.</hi> He gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds us and proſpers us. Eye him, imitate him, keep him near us, with us, within us, and then we ſhall be <hi>more then Conquerours through him that hath loved us.</hi> He only who died for Sin, can be the death of Sin in thee.</p>
               <p>16. Finally, <hi>Think much of your laſt Enemy Death,</hi> with whom alſo you muſt combate, and this part of your Warr will give you a full diſchage from all the Reſt. It becomes Chriſts Souldiers to be no ſtrangers to death, who are called ſo often to Face it, and ever to carry their Lives in their Hands.</p>
               <p>And you aged Chriſtians, you old, beaten, experienced Souldiers, do not carry all your Experiences with you into the Grave. You have been long acquainted with Satans method and manner of <hi>Fighting,</hi> and verſed in the Stratagems of Warr, you may be of excellent uſe and great bleſſings among a Company of young Beginners, ſpend what you may of the little Time that is left you in inſtructing, informing and encourageing thoſe that have as yet learnt but a little Warr. Your Gifts and Experiences were given you to profit withal, and therefore did the Lord help and comfort you, that you might communicate to others for their Aſſiſtance, what he hath been pleaſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100070:17"/> to impart to you. And it will much conduce to your comfortable laying down your Heads in the Grave, that you ſhall leave others behind you who are engaged in the ſame <hi>Warr</hi> with your ſelves, and likely through Grace to manage it well.</p>
               <p>2. By way of Encouragement, let me add a few words.</p>
               <p>And Suppoſe you heard our <hi>Great Captain</hi> ſpeaking theſe words to us this day, to hearten us in our work; and if any need <hi>Heartening Courage</hi> and <hi>Encouragement,</hi> it is the <hi>Souldier,</hi> and if any <hi>Souldier</hi> it's the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> unto whom it had need often be ſaid, as <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35. 3, 4. Then (<hi>Fellow Souldiers</hi>) let us know;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>We have a good General,</hi> one that is <hi>Skilful, able, Compaſſionate,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> who when all the <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>Sin, Luſt,</hi> &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are gathered together againſt us, and the <hi>Devil</hi> the Leader of the <hi>Black <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ard,</hi> he can <hi>Command</hi> and <hi>Countermand</hi> them all.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>We have a good Cauſe,</hi> The Warr with Sin and Satan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a iuſt and lawful Warr, and alſo profitable, no plunder like the profit to be had in this Warr.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>We have good Company, good Fellow Souldiers,</hi> all of them like the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of a King, nay indeed they are ſuch.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>We a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e all well Armed,</hi> each part Armed, and the Armor of each part <hi>Impenetrable.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Our Enemies are already conquered by Chriſt Jeſus our General.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>We Warr not at our own Charge.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Nor in our own Strength,</hi> for in the hotteſt and ſharpeſt diſpute, we have our <hi>Leader</hi> with us, ordering matters himſelf, and affording us ſtrength from himſelf. He is with us in the <hi>Fight,</hi> be it in <hi>Fire, water, Furnace,</hi> &amp;c. ſee <hi>Iſai. 43. 1, 2. Dan.</hi> 3. He is like that <hi>Commander</hi> who was never wont to bid his <hi>Souldiers [Goe]</hi> but [<hi>Come</hi>] himſelf being ever preſent with them, and going before them. ſee <hi>Rom. 8. 31, 37. Pſal. 118. 7. Heb. 13. 5. Pſal. 18. 1, 2. 1 Joh.</hi> 4. 4.</item>
                  <item>8. <hi>If we are indeed his Souldiers, he will preſerve us and ſee us all forth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Have we given up our Names to him, believed on him, then be will keep what we commit to him till that day,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 12. He can, and does warrant all our lives throughout the whole <hi>Warr,</hi> which no <hi>General</hi> on Earth can do. All that <hi>Fight</hi> for, and with Chriſt, ſhall live with him. Say not, I <hi>ſhall one day fall by the hand of</hi> Saul, Thou ſhalt never <hi>fall by the hand of</hi> Saul, nor <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> neither. Let no mans heart fail then, but <hi>be of good Courage,</hi> Act. 27. 22. <hi>Not a man of you ſhall loſe his Life.</hi> Numb. 31. 49. After that Ingagement with <hi>Midian</hi> in the Wilderneſs, it's ſaid, <hi>they numbred the people, and there lack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d not one. When the Book of Life, the Muſter-Roll, in which the Names of all Chriſts Souldiers are liſted,</hi> comes to be brought forth and opened at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100070:17"/> end of the <hi>Warr,</hi> if our Names are there we ſhall be called over, and every one be able to Anſwer to his Name. Let us but <hi>know that our Redeemer lives,</hi> Job. 19. and then, <hi>becauſe he lives, we ſhall,</hi> Joh. 14. 19. And what ſhould then dau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t us? His Life for ours we ſhall all be ſafe. No ſooner are we liſted, but all our Lives, yea, the lives of our <hi>Immortal, Souls</hi> are <hi>enſured</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt's Life</hi> is the <hi>pledge</hi> and <hi>pawn</hi> for ours, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11. 25, 26. who would not <hi>Fight</hi> under ſuch a <hi>Commander?</hi> Our <hi>Captain</hi> cannot die, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> was once dead, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is now alive, and lives for ever and ever,</hi> Rev. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. he dies no more, and his Life is the <hi>Security</hi> for ours.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Chear up <hi>Fellow-Souldiers,</hi> take heart in <hi>Grace:</hi> it's true we have many Enemies, many <hi>Swords, Pikes, Bullets</hi> about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, the <hi>Arrows</hi> flythick, and theſe and thoſe drop down on our <hi>right hand</hi> and <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ft,</hi> but it is with us, as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 23. they that ſeek our Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſeek Chriſts Liſe, but with him we ſhall be in Safety. They that ſeek to take away thine, muſt ſeek, and find, and take away His too, or elſe miſs their Aim, <hi>for thy Life is hid with Chriſt in God,</hi> Col. 3. 3. When Chriſt comes to give an account of his <hi>Souldiers</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his care to the <hi>Father,</hi> he will ſay (as <hi>Joh. 17.) Father I have not loſt one of them,</hi> not one of my <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rue-hearted So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldiers</hi> how weak ſoever, The <hi>Cowards,</hi> the <hi>Traytors</hi> inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d are gone, but not one of the reſt. <hi>Paul</hi> could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, I <hi>have Fought,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo there is a <hi>Crown</hi> for me, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 47. what he ſaid at the end of his Courſe, thou maieſt ſay at the beginning of thine, (for <hi>Chriſt</hi> that is the <hi>Author</hi> is alſo the <hi>Finiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> Heb. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.) and it is as true Divinity to ſay, he that is <hi>Fighting</hi> (in the preſent Tenſe) is ſure to be <hi>crowned,</hi> as he that hath <hi>Fought</hi> in the preterperfect Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe: if <hi>Finiſhing</hi> thou art as ſafe as if thou hadſt <hi>Finiſhed.</hi> If you <hi>Fight the Lords Battels,</hi> your Soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are <hi>bound up in the Bundle of Life,</hi> 1 Sam. 25. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The poor Believer though he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>Hoſt</hi> to break through, where he ſhall be ſure to have <hi>one thouſand Swords</hi> drawn, <hi>Guns levelled, Pikes directed</hi> at him, yet is ſure to ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, he that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries him on, is obliged to bring him off with <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Safety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>9 <hi>Our Warfare ſhall not laſt long, much loſs alwayes.</hi> It was a <hi>comfortable word</hi> to them, and ſhould be to us, [<hi>your Warfare is accompl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhed</hi>] I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 40. 1, 2. Yet a little while and <hi>Friendly Death</hi> (a <hi>welcome Meſſenger</hi> to every <hi>warfaring Chriſtian</hi>) ſhall in the Name of the <hi>Captain</hi> command you to ſay down your <hi>Arms,</hi> never to ſtrike one <hi>bloody blow</hi> more, but to come and enjoy the ſweet of all that you have been labouring and <hi>Fighting</hi> for. And then will be the firſt and laſt Time that this word [lay down your <hi>Arms.</hi>] ſhall be heard by you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> firſt, for you muſt <hi>Fight</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, laſt, for you ſhall never take them up more, and ſo have no occaſion to lay them down any more. The <hi>Goſpel</hi> hath been <hi>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nding</hi> a <hi>Chang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s all our Life Time, but <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſhall <hi>ſound</hi> a <hi>Retreat,</hi> when we ſhall return to the <hi>Head-Quarters</hi> that our <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ral</hi> hath taken up, and prepared for u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>3.) and there be fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſafely lodged for ever.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:100070:18"/>
               <p>10. <hi>We ſhall then be all Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed that have been thus Fighting. The Senate of Heaven hath decreed a Triumph for every Overcomer,</hi> Heb. 12. 1, 2. Not only the <hi>Generals, Commanders,</hi> ſoone few eminent Chriſtians, but every <hi>Common Souldier</hi> ſhall ride into the <hi>Cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, the heavenly Ieruſalem</hi> in his <hi>Triumphant Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> laden with the <hi>Spo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls</hi> of his <hi>Enemies,</hi> and <hi>crowned</hi> with the <hi>Merits</hi> of his <hi>Saviour.</hi> Every true, hardy, couragious Souldier ſhall then be found to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an <hi>Overcomer,</hi> every <hi>Overcomer</hi> ſhall have a <hi>Crown,</hi> every <hi>Crown</hi> ſhall be a <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> an <hi>incorruptible crown,</hi> now reſerved, then put on, and worn, and that <hi>never ſhall fade, or wear away.</hi> Oh think how <hi>Heaven</hi> ſhall <hi>ring</hi> with that <hi>joyful Shout,</hi> thoſe <hi>heart-raviſhing Acclamations</hi> that ſhall then be given, when all the whole <hi>Army</hi> of the <hi>Church-Militant</hi> ſhall meet and become <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant!</hi> How ſhall they <hi>congratulate</hi> one another, and Chriſt welcome them all, into the Poſſeſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of that <hi>Kingdome prepared for them from before the Foundation of the World!</hi> There will be opportunity enough to all <hi>Eternity</hi> to recount their dangers, their <hi>hard Encounters</hi> and <hi>narrow ſcape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> how often there was but a ſtep between them and death, and yet they are ſafe. Then ſhall God have the Glory of his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> in keeping them <hi>through Faith unto Salvation;</hi> that though they were ſo often, and ſo often at the <hi>Swords point,</hi> at the Canons mouth, yet they came off, ſo many <hi>Ambuſhments</hi> laid, and yet not ſurprized<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo many <hi>Mines</hi> ſprung, and yet not blown up, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> holding them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Bondage</hi> with all his might, when out, following them to bring them back, the <hi>red Sea</hi> before them, oft ready to periſh for <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>thirſt,</hi> fiery flying Serpents, Enemies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the wilderneſs, <hi>Iordan</hi> in their way, <hi>Anakims</hi> and walls to Heaven, yet being helped <hi>to follow the Lord fully, couragiouſly,</hi> as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <hi>Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> did, they ſhall ſay, when <hi>Poſſest of Glory,</hi> as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did, Chap 23. 14. <hi>Behold not one good thing is failed of all that the Lord in his word ſpake concerning us, or promiſed to us. Encourage and comfort your ſelves, and one another with theſe words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall cloſe with a few words to thoſe that have been the Occaſion of this preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt Aſſembly, and what I ſay to you, may be of uſe to all of like <hi>Profeſſion</hi> with your ſelves.</p>
               <p>You called me hither, (<hi>Worſhipful, Honoured and Beloved</hi>) that I might (to give it in your own words) diſpenſe to you ſome word in the Name of the Lord for your Incouragement in your work; I ſhall therefore according to your deſire preſent you with a word of Incouragement, and a word of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="encouragement">
               <head>By way of Incouragement, my Text ha's matter enough.</head>
               <p>1. I need not inſiſt largely on (though my Text will bear it,) the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> and <hi>com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endableneſs</hi> of your Imployment as Souldiers, which yet may be mentioned as a word of Encouragement to you; and that is hinted here and elſewhere in the Scripture where the Lord makes uſe of this as one of the moſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100070:18"/> fit, ſuitable and <hi>ſignificant Emblems</hi> of a Chriſtian Life, which he would not do, at leaſt ſo much, if the Calling it ſelf were not lawful. There is a <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> that call theſe Exerciſes <hi>carnal E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erciſes,</hi> and your <hi>Weapons car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al VVeapons,</hi> but God hath ſaid enough in his Word to ſtop the mouths of ſuch <hi>Gainſayers,</hi> and I am apt to think that one main Reaſon why they call theſe <hi>weapons, carnal weapons,</hi> is becauſe they be not in their own Hands, though if there, I fear they would be <hi>car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al weapons</hi> indeed, and it may be carnally and cruelly uſed; Witneſs the Stories of others that have pretended to like Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, till opportunity hath given them Advantage to diſcover themſelves.</p>
               <p>Indeed the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Warr that we read of in Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> Gen. 14 was begun by thoſe that we have no ground to believe were any of the beſt of men, yet that gave occaſion to <hi>Abraham</hi> that <hi>holy, rightsous, Pattern-Believer</hi> to draw the Sword in the ſame Chapter, having before hand prudently trained up his Servants unto <hi>Military Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes,</hi> that they might be fit to go forth to Warr when Providence ſhould put them upon it. (<hi>ver.</hi> 14.) The word there ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred [<hi>trained</hi>] doth not only ſignifie trained up in <hi>Religious E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion,</hi> as it is uſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. 6. But alſo initiated or inſtructed in <hi>Military <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kill,</hi> as the Scope of the place, beſides the Senſe of the word ſeems plainly and fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to carry it. So that as <hi>Abraham</hi> was the <hi>Great Pattern Believer,</hi> ſo he was in this Chapter the <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eat Pattern-Souldier, exemplary</hi> and <hi>imitable</hi> both in training up his men before hand to have them ready, and alſo in leading them forth to actual Service when there was occaſion. Nor need any of the Children of <hi>Abraham</hi> (as all Believers are) doubt to imitate (rather they are to account themſelves obliged to imitate) their <hi>Father</hi> in that which is ſo many wayes warranted, and wherein he was ſo <hi>proſpered</hi> and <hi>ſucceeded,</hi> and upon his return from which ſo <hi>extraordinarily, bleſſed,</hi> as you find in the ſame Chapter. Sure the Lords ſo bleſſing him upon ſuch a <hi>warlike Exploit</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates his acceptance of him therein, and helps to <hi>warrantiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the like practiſe to us.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>David was a man after Gods own heart,</hi> and yet <hi>a man of warr,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 17. 8. Had his <hi>mighty men</hi> trained to Service, about him, made a Law in <hi>Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> thereabout, 2 Sam. 1. 18. that there ſhould be <hi>Training daies</hi> (as we call them) Times ſet apart to teach the <hi>Art</hi> of Souldiery. The <hi>Bow</hi> being a <hi>principal Instrument</hi> then uſed in Warr, is <hi>Syn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chdochically<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> put for every weapon of warr, and their learning the uſe of that, intends their Skill in the whole Art. <hi>Solomon</hi> in his beſt dayes, and before his Apoſtaoy, though a <hi>King of peace,</hi> yet provided <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or Warr, and ſo did <hi>Aſa,</hi> 2 Chron. 140, 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he took the Advantage of the peaceable dayes they had to fit themſelves for warr. So they are commended for their ability to keep Rank, and uſe the Sword with both hands, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 38.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Benjamites skill</hi> in ſlinging Stones at an <hi>Hairs-breadth</hi> is upon Record
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100070:19"/> to their <hi>Commendation,</hi> and ſure they had not that Skill <hi>naturally,</hi> but by uſe and Exerciſe.</p>
               <p>You find alſo that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> when about the wall of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had his <hi>Fighting Tool</hi> in one hand, and <hi>working Tool</hi> in the other, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. 17.</p>
               <p>Let me add a place or two out of the <hi>New-Testam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt,</hi> Luk. 3 14 when the <hi>Souldiers</hi> came to <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and asked what they ſhould do, he bids them not lay down their Arms, but uſe them well, not <hi>violently, injuriouſly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and to be content with their wages,</hi> though to take wages, i. e the <hi>wages</hi> or <hi>Stipend</hi> of <hi>Souldiers,</hi> though to do the work of Souldiers, elſe it had not been lawful or rational to take wages, though the Calling &amp; Imployment of <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> is lawful. Some in our dayes would have ſaid, man thou maieſt not <hi>Fight,</hi> thou muſt not meddle with that <hi>Profeſſion</hi> any more, it is not lawful for thee to be a <hi>Souldier,</hi> but the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> knew better.</p>
               <p>The <hi>godly Centurion</hi> that had not his <hi>Fellow</hi> for a Believer in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> did not lay down his place, give up his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> or <hi>disband</hi> his <hi>Souldiers</hi> (which doubtleſs he would have done if it had not been lawful to be a Souldier) no, but he keeps up good Diſcipline among them, maintains his <hi>Authority,</hi> and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them at his <hi>Beck,</hi> Math. 8 8, 10. You read alſo of <hi>Armies</hi> following <hi>Christ on white Horſes,</hi> Rev. 19. 14. I might further urge it from the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>f Preſervation</hi> is one of the <hi>Prime Dictates</hi> of <hi>Nature.</hi> It is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetted into our very <hi>Beings</hi> as <hi>Creatures</hi> to preſerve our ſelves, we muſt <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creature</hi> our ſelves if we renounce that. Sure God hath not given to all other Creatures an <hi>Inſtinct</hi> to preſerve themſelves, (ſome by <hi>hiding,</hi> ſome by <hi>flying,</hi> others by <hi>Fighting,</hi> &amp;c.) and in the mean Time left man like a <hi>tame Fool</hi> to be a <hi>Prey</hi> to his <hi>Adverſary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, The <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> ſpeaks the ſame thing, for it doth moſt ſtrongly and <hi>indiſpenſibly</hi> put upon the uſe of means. <hi>Abraham</hi> could (for ought I know) believe as much as any man alive, even <hi>in hope againſt hope,</hi> and yet <hi>Abraham</hi> could not <hi>believe</hi> Lot <hi>out of Captivity,</hi> (though be could <hi>believe</hi> Iſaac <hi>out of the aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi>) but rather choſe to uſe men and means to <hi>Fight him out.</hi> This <hi>Great Believer</hi> was <hi>great Souldier.</hi> It is true, the main Security of the Believers is their <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> but ſtill in his own way, <hi>viz.</hi> in the uſe of means where God gives opportunity, without doing of which you cannot truſt God. He knows not the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> that knows not the <hi>activity</hi> of it in the uſe of means. <hi>Faith</hi> is a moſt <hi>Active, obedient Grace.</hi> You ſpoil its acting while you are not found in a way of <hi>Obedience.</hi> In putting it out of that way you <hi>ham ſtring, enervate,</hi> it, <hi>clipp</hi> its <hi>wings,</hi> and then how can you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it ſhould <hi>goe, act fly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We might argue alſo from the <hi>unreaſonable, envious, quarrelſome, injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, cruel,</hi> yea, <hi>murtherous Spirit</hi> that is in <hi>ſinfulman,</hi> which will not be kept from doing wrong but by ſuch means. Were all men <hi>rational</hi> and <hi>Religious,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100070:19"/> Conſcientious</hi> and <hi>pious,</hi> then <hi>beat their Swords into plow-Shares,</hi> &amp;c. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, and the <hi>Royal Law</hi> of <hi>doing as we would be done by,</hi> would ſecure all mens perſons and Eſtates; but <hi>all men have not Faith,</hi> nor <hi>love,</hi> nor <hi>ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> nor do they uſe <hi>Conſcience</hi> neither. The <hi>enm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty between the ſeed of the Serpent and the woman,</hi> which appeared betimes in the Example of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> and inclined the one to <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tred</hi> and <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> ſhould prompt the other to <hi>ſelf-preſervation</hi> and the means of it.</p>
               <p>What <hi>Warr</hi> is <hi>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ful</hi> and when, I ſhall not diſpute, but that a <hi>Defenſive Warr</hi> is <hi>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ful</hi> is beyond diſpute, to <hi>Fight</hi> for the <hi>Citties</hi> of our God, as 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 12. or to recover ours out of the <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>violence,</hi> as <hi>Gen.</hi> 14, So <hi>Jep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thah</hi> went to <hi>Warr</hi> againſt thoſe that would have put him out of the <hi>Inheritance which God had given him,</hi> Jude 11. and he was one of thoſe that acted in <hi>Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h,</hi> Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 33, 34. together with others there mentioned, while <hi>ſabduing Kingdomes, waving valiant in F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght, and turning to flight the Armies of the Aliens.</hi> Chriſts forbidding to <hi>reſist evil,</hi> Math. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 39 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> refers to private perſons in a <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Revenge,</hi> vid. <hi>Perkins in loc.</hi> Nor had <hi>Peter</hi> a Call at that Time to <hi>reſiſt Authority</hi> in that way, <hi>Math.</hi> 26. 52. who was therefore bidden to put up his <hi>Sword,</hi> and they are threatned to <hi>periſh with the Sword</hi> that do <hi>anſeaſonably</hi> and <hi>injuriouſly</hi> uſe it. Not but that the <hi>Civil Power</hi> may, and ought draw the <hi>Sword</hi> in Caſe. It's true, we read of a <hi>Curſe</hi> againſt them that <hi>delight in Warr,</hi> Pſal. 68. 30. and no leſs are they <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> that come not to the <hi>Help of the Lord againſt the mighty,</hi> Jud. 5. and do but only <hi>beat the Air,</hi> and not bath their Swords in Blood when they do come, <hi>Jer.</hi> 48. 10. That then is the firſt word of Encouragement to you in your work, <hi>viz.</hi> that you have good warrant, <hi>Scripture warrant</hi> for your <hi>Training dayes</hi> and <hi>Military Exerciſes,</hi> and that the Lord doth <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>require</hi> theſe <hi>preparations,</hi> that you may be ready to ſerve the Lord and his people, when he calls you thereunto.</p>
               <p>2. A ſecond word of Encouragement which I may add, and that from my Text, is that <hi>Great</hi> is the <hi>Honour</hi> which the Lord puts upon you as <hi>Military perſons,</hi> eſpecially in ſuch a <hi>Capacity</hi> as thoſe that do willingly give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Service of God in ſuch <hi>Exerciſes,</hi> and that not only in that he ſpeaks of the Saints, (<hi>the excellent ones upon Earth</hi>) in your language, but alſo in that the Lord is often in Scripture calling himſelf <hi>the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> ſo alſo <hi>a Man of Warr,</hi> Exod. 15. 3. The Son of God alſo is <hi>Captain-General,</hi> (as <hi>Mediatour</hi>) under his <hi>Father,</hi> ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 1-5. Beſides the moſt <hi>eminent</hi> of the Saints all along have been Souldiers, (I mean properly ſo) <hi>Father Abra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am</hi> was free of the <hi>Souldiers-Hall,</hi> and had an <hi>Artillery Garden</hi> at his houſe, <hi>three hundred</hi> and <hi>eighteen</hi> in his <hi>trained Band,</hi> Gen. 14 14. <hi>Dav'd</hi> in like manner, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 8. Indeed, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all the Saints upon Earth are of your <hi>Company,</hi> which is much for your <hi>Honour.</hi> Again, much of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100070:20"/> the Scripture is ſpent about Souldiers, and Souldiery. How many <hi>Chapters</hi> in Sacred Writ are no other but ſo many <hi>Liſts</hi> of the <hi>Names</hi> of Souldiers that have been in <hi>former Ages,</hi> and how many more are ſpent in reciring the <hi>noble Exploits</hi> and <hi>valorous Attempts</hi> and <hi>Enterprizes</hi> of Souldiers? Twice over in two ſeveral <hi>Chapters,</hi> viz. 2 Sam. 23. and 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11. are the Names of <hi>Davids</hi> choice, expert Souldiers, called his <hi>Worthies,</hi> ſet down. Beſides a <hi>large Catalogue</hi> of the <hi>mighty men</hi> that helped <hi>David</hi> is expreſt, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. the <hi>expert Commanders</hi> and able Souldiers that came in to them, till they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a <hi>great Host</hi> like the <hi>Hoſt of God,</hi> ver. 22. Now to have ſuch <hi>frequent</hi> and Honourable mention made of Souldiers in the Word of God, and to have ſo <hi>conſiderable</hi> a part of it ſo ſpent, is a <hi>great Honour</hi> to Souldiers, and ſhews the great delight that <hi>the Lora of Hoſts</hi> hath in his Souldiery, it tells us that they are perſons <hi>whom the Lord delights to Honour,</hi> And Honour is a good En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and Spurt to a Souldier. Your Imployment is no <hi>baſe, low, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Imployment,</hi> but one <hi>highly honoured by the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Souldiers, know that the Lord hath put a great deal of <hi>Honour</hi> upon you, for which you are exceedingly beholden to him; carry it <hi>humbly, thankfully,</hi> and <hi>ſerviceably</hi> toward God under the <hi>Honour</hi> He conferrs upon you. See that you <hi>Honour</hi> him, who thus <hi>honoureth</hi> you. If <hi>God will Honour thoſe that Honour him,</hi> (1 Sam. 2. 30.) Then ſurely thoſe ſhould <hi>honour him whom he bonours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. A third word of Encouragement I ſhall take from the great uſe that God hath all along made of <hi>Military men</hi> in his Church. To be uſeful and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable is an <hi>Honour,</hi> (for the <hi>more ſerviceable</hi> the <hi>more Honourable</hi>) eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be ſo <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>immediately ſerviceable</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church,</hi> as Souldiers have been, yea, are, and ſhall be even to the very laſt. And this is a further Encouragement. Though properly the Lord needs no help <hi>againſt the mighty,</hi> yet he uſes them, and one Reaſon is for the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> of them that he uſes. Chriſt may make uſe of you to be great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in the places where you live. It is a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to a people to have <hi>mighty men</hi> and <hi>men of Warr</hi> among them, as appears, becauſe it is a great judgement to have ſuch taken away from them, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3. Be encouraged then, for you are uſeful, and may be made <hi>great Bleſſings,</hi> and that is a <hi>bleſſed thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. <hi>Great is the Affection that God ha's for ſueb, eſpecially for them that offer themſelves willingly unto that ſervice.</hi> (provided that their Hearts be right therein, for the Service and Glory of God,) Gods heart is toward ſuch as <hi>Deborah's</hi> was, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5. 9. Now that Gods heart is toward you, and preſence with you, while you are with, and for Him, is a very <hi>comfortable, heartening,</hi> and <hi>encouraging word</hi> to be ſpoken at the <hi>Head</hi> of an <hi>Army,</hi> ſee <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chron.</hi> 15. 2.</p>
               <p>5. The main Scope of the whole that I have ſpoken may be improved by way of Encouragement, <hi>viz.</hi> that you are both much inlightned about the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of, and furthered in the managing of your <hi>General Calling</hi> as Chriſtians by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100070:20"/> your being Souldiers. As your Chriſtianity will help your Souldiery, ſo be ſure your Souldiery (if the fault b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not your own) will noteably help your Chriſtianity. Every <hi>Training-day</hi> may be a <hi>learning day</hi> to you, while trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you may be working for God and Chriſt, and for your Souls too. If your Soul-work may go forward amain while you are <hi>exerciſing</hi> your <hi>Arms,</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be a <hi>great Encouragement</hi> to them that know they have Souls, and know the worth of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. You that are Souldiers (as I have already hinted) are eminently beholden to God in that he is <hi>full, large,</hi> and <hi>particular</hi> in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualizing your Calling, in putting ſo much of Heaven thereinto, that if you will ſeriouſly attend, you cannot but find it. Truly our going with an Earthly, mind about our Earthly work, with a <hi>common Heart</hi> about our <hi>common Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,</hi> is that which ſpoils us in it, and maakes us loſe the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſt Good,</hi> even the <hi>ſpiritual Good</hi> that might be gotten thereby.</p>
               <p>Unto this word of Encouragement, I ſhall add a few words of Advice.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Propoſe right Ends to your ſelves in theſe Exerciſes.</hi> There are good and uſeful Ends of them, let thoſe <hi>good Ends</hi> be your Ends. If your Ends are not right, you may be Souldiers but ſcarce Chriſtians. Now the <hi>Great End</hi> of all our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings,</hi> and of this in ſpecial, is <hi>the Glory of God. Whatſoever you do, do it to the Glory of God,</hi> (1 Cor. 10. 31.) Let the Service of God and his Church be the mark you aim at, the white which you deſire and endeavour to hitt, which if you do you ſhall be ſure to get the prize. Had we never read ought of <hi>Ioab</hi> ſave that one Speech, a Sam. 10. 12. we ſhould have in Charity accounted him not only a Souldier, (as we ſay) every Inch of him, but a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man alſo; However he deſerves to be <hi>Chronicled</hi> for it, and <hi>imitated</hi> in it. [<hi>For our people and for the Citties of our God</hi>] Come not into the Field to ſhew your Bravery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but come to do Service, to learn Sk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for further Service. Do not Exerciſe that you may know, or be known to know, but that you may do, and do for the people and Cauſe of God and Chriſt, for whom to ſhed your Blood, is the beſt way to preſerve it, to lay down your Lives, the beſt way to ſave them.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Then be ſerious in your work,</hi> as thoſe that have ſo high an End, and mean to do you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> utmoſt to attain that End; If this be your End, then do not go about you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> work like men <hi>that beat the Air.</hi> I may uſe the Apoſties Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and propoſe his Example to you, (For your ultimate End in your <hi>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ticular Calling</hi> is the ſame with his in his <hi>General Calling</hi> and your Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in every Buſineſs and in this eſpecially, is to have the ſame Common End) <hi>ſo run that you may obtain the priz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>,</hi> and ſo labour not <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> uncertainly,</hi> and ſo meet, Exerciſe, train, (as you call it] <hi>not as thoſe that beat the Air.</hi> God makes uſe of your Calling as Souldiers to ſet forrh the Calling of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by, a Calling wherein the greateſt accurateneſs, exactneſs, Care, Skill, Diligence is to be uſed: then ſo do your work, ſo mind your Buſineſs, that as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100070:21"/> Religion <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onours</hi> your <hi>Calling,</hi> ſo your exactneſs and compleatneſs in your <hi>Calling</hi> may <hi>honour</hi> that Religion which you proſeſs, and which <hi>honours</hi> your <hi>Profeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You called me hither to ſpeak to you a word in the <hi>Name</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> then, <hi>In the Name of the Lord</hi> I ſay to you in the words of my Text, again, be not like thoſe <hi>that beat the Air,</hi> and in the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 9. 10. <hi>what ever your Hand findeth to do, do it with your might.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You <hi>much Intereſt</hi> or <hi>concern</hi> the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in your <hi>Military Exerciſes,</hi> you <hi>Invocate</hi> the <hi>Name</hi> of God in the morning when you come together, you deſire ſomething to be ſpoken to you <hi>in the Name of God</hi> upon theſe Occaſions, then, in his <hi>Name,</hi> I beſeech you to hear what is now ſpoken in his <hi>Name, viz.</hi> Play the <hi>men,</hi> not the <hi>children,</hi> not the <hi>Fools.</hi> To pray for the preſence of God when you go about a Buſineſs, and then to play when you are at it, not to be <hi>thorough</hi> and <hi>ſerious</hi> in it, is to pray God to come among you to ſee you play the <hi>children</hi> or <hi>Fools,</hi> as if the <hi>infinitely holy and wiſe God</hi> would be <hi>pleaſed with the Sacrifice of Fools,</hi> Eccleſ. 5. 1. (which Text though it relates principally to worſhip, yet it holds by proportion in any thing that is called ſerving of God.) To ſupplicate Gods preſence, and then to take no Care to do ought worthy of his preſence, to deſire God to look on, when you have nothing but a <hi>vain Heart,</hi> and a <hi>ſlighty, heedleſs Carriage</hi> to ſhew him, how near this comes to <hi>mocking of God</hi> you may <hi>ſadly Conſider.</hi> God is a <hi>man of Warr,</hi> and delights to be among ſuch, to deign them his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence when they deſire it, but <hi>I</hi> tell you he hath a <hi>Curious</hi> and <hi>skilful eye,</hi> and therefore it becomes you to behave your ſelves as becomes his preſence. I have ſeen ſome <hi>Artillery men</hi> as really <hi>ſerious</hi> when they have been at training as when they have been at prayer, and ſo to be is very pleaſing both to God and man.</p>
               <p>I ſhall make bold to inſiſt a little upon this Direction; Here is a <hi>Great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly</hi> and <hi>many Souldiers</hi> are preſent from all parts, it may not therefore be amiſs and unſeaſonable to give ſomething by way of <hi>General Direction</hi> unto what is <hi>regular,</hi> and of <hi>Reprehenſion</hi> to what is otherwiſe, in this matter now before us.</p>
               <p>It is too <hi>palpable</hi> and <hi>obvious</hi> not to be taken notice of, that there is a great deal of <hi>ſlightineſs</hi> and <hi>frothineſs</hi> in <hi>Military Exerciſes,</hi> or in men, while <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant</hi> in thoſe <hi>Exerciſes;</hi> Your <hi>ordinary Training dayes</hi> are accounted <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation-dayes, play-dayes, ſporting-dayes,</hi> and they are oft, and by many, ſpent in <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>Licentiouſneſs,</hi> as if <hi>vain merriment, Idleneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Exceſs</hi> were the work of the day, as if there would be no <hi>reckoning</hi> for ſo many dayes in a year <hi>unprofitably ſpent,</hi> nay, as if there would be no <hi>reckoning</hi> for mens taking occaſion to <hi>make Proviſion for the Fleſh</hi> at ſuch Times when they ſhould be Serving God, not with their <hi>Bodies</hi> only, but with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100070:21"/> their <hi>Spirits</hi> alſo. But ſuppoſe there be not, (as I hope among your ſelves there is not, you pretend to higher things, and I hope better things of you though I thus ſpeak) I ſay, ſuppoſe there be not any of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe <hi>Extravagancies,</hi> yet how will you be able to Anſwer for <hi>bare non Profici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncy,</hi> and for <hi>ſlighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>heedliſsneſs,</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Know, that when you have <hi>given up your Names</hi> unto ſuch a work, then to neglect <hi>Attendance,</hi> either not to come at all, or to come late, to ſtudy, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cuſes</hi> for your <hi>neglect,</hi> to be among your <hi>ſheep, ſhips,</hi> &amp;c. as they, <hi>Iud.</hi> 5. 16, 17. you may poſſibly ſave your <hi>Fine</hi> among men, but with God will not come off ſo eaſily. Or if you do come, and that in Seaſon, ſo as not to be <hi>prickt</hi> for want of Anſwering to your <hi>Names,</hi> and ſpend the day in the Service, and yet not ſo <hi>ſeriouſly intenſly, heedfully,</hi> as to make ſome <hi>Addition</hi> to you <hi>skill</hi> or <hi>Dexterity</hi> by every dayes expence, how will you be able when called to account for that day, (and every day is a <hi>Talent</hi> and muſt be reckoned for) to ſay, Lord that much gained.</p>
               <p>Oh let not Souldiers be like <hi>ſchool-Boyes,</hi> as not to care how little they have for their <hi>Mony,</hi> how little Time at their Books, or how little good they get in that Time. Be not <hi>ever Training</hi> and never <hi>gaining</hi> any <hi>skill</hi> by the <hi>Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Better ſtay at home and work, then come into the <hi>Field</hi> and play, to ſpend Time and get no <hi>skill,</hi> nor perhaps aim to get any, will not paſs for well ſpending of Time. You <hi>Artillery men</hi> ſhould be <hi>Artists</hi> indeed, each of you Able to <hi>drill</hi> a <hi>Company,</hi> to lead an <hi>Army,</hi> able to keep <hi>Rank</hi> your ſelves, and teach others to do ſo too, your being an <hi>Artillery Company</hi> ſpeaks that you are, and aim to be ſomewhat more then <hi>Ordinary.</hi> And truly you will never do as you ought to do, till you make Conſcience of doing as you ought. <hi>Conſcience</hi> of <hi>duty</hi> will make you <hi>attend duty,</hi> and be <hi>intenſe</hi> in your <hi>Attendance;</hi> the way to be <hi>ſucceſsful</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>It's a <hi>Good Rule</hi> in any <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> (and ſurely in yours) to argue thus, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this is <hi>Gods work</hi> that I am about, or not; if not, lay it aſide, give over, take your <hi>Names</hi> but of the <hi>Liſt,</hi> wholly <hi>withdraw,</hi> appear no more; but if it be <hi>Gods work,</hi> then <hi>do it with your might,</hi> remembring the <hi>workleſs grave</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which you are <hi>marching,</hi> as alſo the danger you are in of that <hi>dreadful Sentence</hi> againſt the <hi>deceitful dealer</hi> in Gods Service, <hi>Ier.</hi> 48. 10. You are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>ſerious</hi> in your <hi>deportment. Gravity</hi> in a Souldier eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly while in Service, is very commendable. It's a <hi>weighty work</hi> that you are about, and getting <hi>skill</hi> therein, may be as much as your Lives are worth. Matters of Life and death are <hi>ſolemn, ponderous matters,</hi> (and theſe are, or you know not how ſoon they may be ſuch, what ever men think of them) and therefore to be <hi>gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ely managed. Edge Tools</hi> are not to be plaid with. Over much <hi>lightneſs</hi> in mens Hearts and Spirits a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d want of being <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate,</hi> oft Times occaſion much miſchief, in theſe <hi>Exerciſes. Frequent Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> ſhew us what comes of <hi>raſhneſs</hi> and <hi>rudeneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Youthful vanity, precipita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100070:22"/> jeſtings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ollck</hi> have (and that not unuſually) <hi>ſorrowful Cataſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phes, ſad</hi> and and <hi>better Concluſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Souldiers have no Law for being lawleſs. <hi>Headineſs</hi> and <hi>Hastineſs</hi> makes way for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce</hi> at <hi>leiſure,</hi> when he that walks <hi>gravely</hi> and <hi>regularly</hi> walke <hi>ſafely,</hi> and ſo ſpares himſelf that labour. Then mind your Buſineſs, as thoſe that know it is <hi>Gods buſineſs,</hi> mind your work at thoſe that have a mind to work, and to be gaining by their work.</p>
               <p>Mind and attend to the word of Command, which you cannot do while <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing, ſmokeing,</hi> and <hi>chatting away</hi> this Time; want of mens giving up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the work when they are at it, becauſe they do not <hi>Hoc agere,</hi> not give heed to what is commanded, and ſo by them to be done, I ſay, this is the Cauſe why often Times they are ſo <hi>unhandy</hi> at their Buſineſs, and ſo <hi>unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> in performing their <hi>poſtures,</hi> do not keep <hi>Rank</hi> and <hi>File,</hi> are routed in their <hi>marches, Counter, marches, doublings, wheelings,</hi> all in a <hi>huddle</hi> and <hi>ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly diſordered. Heedleſsneſs</hi> in work makes <hi>confuſed work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Excuſe my plainneſs with you, I cannot charge any of your ſelves upon my own <hi>Knowledge</hi> with theſe diſorders that have been reproved, if any are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, thoſe that deſerve, may very well patiently bear Reproof; thoſe that do not deſerve it, may well be quiet, while others are reproved that do, and may alſo take it as a word of <hi>Caution</hi> to themſelves, yea, and <hi>Commendation</hi> too; for a <hi>Reprehenſion</hi> to the Guilty is <hi>implicitely</hi> a <hi>Commendation</hi> to them that are otherwiſe. But thus be in good earneſt.</p>
               <p>Perhaps your Exerciſes may look like <hi>beating the Air,</hi> becauſe you are not called forth to real Service, but know, that <hi>preparation</hi> for real Service is real Service, and if you do nothing but <hi>beat the Air</hi> now, you will be like to do lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle toward beating your Enemy then. Act ſo in your preparation, that it may appear you have not been trained up for nothing. We read of the Enemies being <hi>skilful to deſtroy,</hi> Ezek <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. 21. which ſpeaks need of our being <hi>skilful to defend.</hi> Study to be <hi>mighty men,</hi> and <hi>men of Warr,</hi> (as <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3.) the <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works</hi> of the place while you live, that you may be as they, 2 <hi>Sam. 1. 17. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably Epita, bed,</hi> and <hi>buterly lamented</hi> when you die. Be <hi>ambitious</hi> of being like to thoſe who are for their <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>valour</hi> recorded in Scripture as <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> of <hi>Imitation,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5. 18. and 12. 8, 21, 30, 32, 33, 38.</p>
               <p>You know not how ſoon the Lord and his people may have occaſion for your Help <hi>againſt the Mighty.</hi> It is true God hath been very kind to <hi>New-England,</hi> no breaking in, nor leading forth, <hi>nor complaining in our Streets,</hi> this laſt year alſo, this <hi>dangerous year,</hi> this <hi>threatning year,</hi> ſo like to prove a <hi>bloody</hi> one to us, as well as to many other places, I ſay, this year is you ſee fairly gone off the <hi>Stage.</hi> We had the laſt week out <hi>Great Solemnity,</hi> our Beginning of a <hi>New Year,</hi> or <hi>New Years day,</hi> wherein we had opportunity of ſetting up our <hi>Eben Ezer</hi> and ſaying, <hi>hitherto God hath helped us.</hi> We may bleſs God and ſay with him, <hi>Pſal. 55. 18. He hath delivered our ſouls in peace from the Battel
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100070:22"/> that was againſt us, for there were many with us.</hi> It is true alſo, that this year be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gins with the Tideings of Peace, we have had the <hi>Dove</hi> ſent in among us with an <hi>Olive leaf</hi> to give us ſome intimation of the <hi>Abatement of the flood,</hi> &amp; Hopes that it may not reach us; And the <hi>God of peace</hi> grant that there may be <hi>Peace</hi> indeed, a well grounded and ſettled Peace: Peace with God firſt, as the Cauſe, and then with men as the Effect, peace with Truth, peace with holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that will be a <hi>firm, long-lasting, everlaſting peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet for all this, I could not ſee Cauſe to preach on that Text, <hi>Iſai. 2. 4. Beat your Swords into Plow-ſhares,</hi> &amp;c. I think rather that of <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 36. or 2 Sam. 1. 18. or <hi>Ioel.</hi> 3. 10. would be more ſuitable. I fear the Nations have not forgotten Warr as yet, nor will they unlearn Warr wholly, till they do unlearn Sin and Luſt more, <hi>from whence their Warrs come,</hi> till pride lower and ſtrike, the Warrs will never end. While there is Fleſh as well as Spirit in the new man, there will be Warrs within; and while there are carnal men as well as Spiritual in the World there will be Warrs without. Therefore while we <hi>pray for the peace of</hi> Jeruſalem, we are to provide for the Wars that will be made againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as knowing that the Church on Earth is the <hi>Church-Militant,</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſhall be a quiet habitation,</hi> but we muſt not <hi>antedare</hi> Gods work. That Time ſhall come, but in the mean Time we muſt handle our Arms, as well as Ploughs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anti-Christ muſt Fall,</hi> and the Enemies of the Church ſhall be overcome by a material Sword, as well as by a Spiritual one. The Prayers of the Saints have long cried, their teares have cried, their blood hath cried, the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells of Chriſt have long yearned over them, and himſelf hath long waited to to ſee his Enemies made <hi>his Footſtool,</hi> and therefore ſure it cannot be long. And what an Honour will it be to be called to that work, and dexterous at it when called to it. When <hi>Abraham</hi> was called to follow God in a way of Reformation, &amp; God had in that way bleſſed him outwardly too, he could not but know that the Enemies about him would envy him not only as Religious, but as proſpering outwardly in a Profeſſion of Religion, which might give him juſt occaſion to train up his Family to Military Diſcipline, as we read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14, 14. that he might be in a poſture ready to receive them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Occaſion ſhould be. We in this Wilderneſs, both on the account of our Profeſſion and Proſperity under it, have long been, and ſtill are an Eye-ſore to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, theſe are, that are conſulting to undermine us, and we ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to ſecure our ſelves, not only by p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aying, that no foot of pride may come againſt us, nor hand of violence move us, but alſo, if any ſuch ſhould come by preparing before hand to give them ſuch a Reception as may diſcover, that as we were <hi>fore-warned,</hi> ſo alſo <hi>fore-armed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Great are the things that a Religious people have to deſend, <hi>viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> beſides their Lives, Liberties, Relation, Eſtates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Name, honour and worſhip
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100070:23"/> of God, the <hi>pleaſant things</hi> of his Houſe, thoſe <hi>Great Betruſtments</hi> which the world cannot boaſt of, and are more worth then all the world; and hence they ſhould labour to furniſh themſelves both with Skil and ability to defend and maintain what God ha's given them, or elſe they will act both <hi>irrationally</hi> for themſelves, and <hi>untbankfully</hi> toward God that hath ſo <hi>priviledged</hi> them. The Faith and the <hi>pleaſant things of Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> are worth contending for, and that not with the tongue and heart only, but with the hands and Sword alſo when God calls thereu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to.</p>
               <p>Great alſo is the Advantage that a people get by being expert for Warr, their being ſo, may be a means to prevent <hi>Warr.</hi> The report of a people's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>warlike people</hi> may be of ſingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r uſe to them, the fame of their skill may be a means to prevent their uſing it. Whereas the Security of a people invites an Enemy, and renders them lyable to be a <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey,</hi> ſee <hi>Judg.</hi> 18. 7, 8, 9.</p>
               <p>Times of peace are Times to prepare for War<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and if we miſs it in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, we ſhall be <hi>fearfully hurried</hi> and <hi>blundred</hi> when we come to action, we cannot promiſe our ſelves to be ſaved then, unleſs we be dilige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration now. If Warr comes, the comfort of having done our duty, and the profit of being in a readineſs, will make amends for the trouble; iſ it comes not, our peace will bear the Charge of our preparation. Thus be <hi>intenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> about, and <hi>ſerious</hi> in theſe <hi>Exerciſes,</hi> make Conſcience of gaining Skill, and of ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Time ſo as may beſt conduce to that End. So do in theſe as well as other matters, as you would be glad to have done when an Enemy comes, yea, when Chriſt ſhall come. Train as in the fight of an Enemy, with whom you may be called to <hi>Fight.</hi> Train as doing Service to Chriſt, and in the fight of Chriſt, who will one day reward every dayes Service, and this dayes Service, if you diligently and obediently ſerve him therein.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Be Spiritual and Heavenly in all your Military Exerciſes, that you may be good Chriſtians as well as good Souldiers.</hi> It is good <hi>policy</hi> and <hi>prudence</hi> for <hi>pious Rulers</hi> to command and Countenance the <hi>training</hi> up thoſe that are under their <hi>Government</hi> unto <hi>Military Skill,</hi> ſo that if need be, they may be able to ſpeak with the <hi>Enemy</hi> in the <hi>Gate,</hi> and under their <hi>approbation</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> you li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Exerciſe your ſelves in theſe Affairs. Will it not then be much more <hi>prudence</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> in every man that ſhould be Maſter of himſelf, to <hi>command</hi> his <hi>whole man</hi> to follow the Lord Jeſus in the <hi>Spiritual Warfare,</hi> to liſt every Faculty and member of Soul and body under Chriſts Command, and deliver them up to his Service, that under his <hi>protection</hi> he may <hi>Fight</hi> and <hi>overcome</hi> his <hi>Spiritual Enemies?</hi> Art thou a Leader, and haſt a Charge of a Company about thee? Conſider then the <hi>great Charge</hi> that is left with thee, as to a <hi>little world</hi> within thee, a <hi>little Army,</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing of Soul with it's Faculties, the Body with it's members, like the <hi>Cavalry</hi> and <hi>Infantry, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> and theſe thou muſt train up in the Art of <hi>Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ual Souldiery.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100070:23"/>
               <p>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>der Command, and to be led by others, then remember that Chriſt the <hi>great General</hi> expects like obedience from thee as the <hi>Cen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urion</hi> had from his Souldiers, <hi>Math.</hi> 8. to <hi>come</hi> and <hi>go</hi> and <hi>do</hi> at his <hi>pleaſure.</hi> He that can <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> that <hi>little Company</hi> of himſelf, and teach every part its proper motions and <hi>Postures</hi> is a <hi>compleat Souldier</hi> indeed. You are labouring to be ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct Souldiers; what, and <hi>bung ling Chriſtians?</hi> Oh for ſhame! what, lead an <hi>Army,</hi> and be <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſled</hi> by a <hi>ſingle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>illy luſt?</hi> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thou know all the <hi>Poſtures</hi> of a Souldier, all the <hi>Facings, Firings, Wheelings,</hi> &amp;c? and yet an <hi>ignorant, dull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Soul</hi> as to <hi>ſpiritual Souldierys</hi> God forbid. Art thou labouring to be a Souldier, and takeſt no Care and Thought to be a <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> how ſad will that be? God expects of all us that live under the Goſpel, that we ſhould be <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry-men,</hi> and he expects of you <hi>Artill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry-men</hi> that you eſpecially ſhould be exact <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as having ſuch a Calling as will greatly advantage you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, in many reſpects above other <hi>Calling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> The very ſight of your <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Weapons</hi> ſhould affect you with ſome Spiritual Conſideration, and the handling of them put you upon like Actions. Your Souldiery and Religion do Border ſo near together, that they are in a <hi>great meaſure</hi> both of <hi>one lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage;</hi> the Chriſtian and the Souldier may, and ought underſtand one another, and both the language and work of the latter will help to <hi>familiari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> that of the former. Take a touch of it in ſome few Inſtances.</p>
               <p>Your liſting of your<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſelves, minds you of that great duty of giving up your <hi>Names</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your <hi>General,</hi> and your doing it <hi>voluntarily,</hi> ſhould put you in mind of, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 3.) and make you pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y heartily, to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> it clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up to you that you are ſome of the people that God in a <hi>day of Power</hi> hath <hi>made willing.</hi> The Souldier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lifting of himſelf is the <hi>Chriſtians Converſion,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from <hi>Sin, Self,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>unto God,</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> and this of <hi>Effectual Vocation</hi> will lead you up to <hi>Election,</hi> and this known, will make <hi>Election</hi> alſo known, ſee (<hi>Rom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. with 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10.) and help you to mad your <hi>Names</hi> in the <hi>Lambs Book of Life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> the Joyes of which Condition, and <hi>Priviledges</hi> belonging unto which, no tongue can tell.</p>
               <p>Upon li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing you are obliged to attend on the Seaſons, &amp; at the places of Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, to do all the duties that the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tring of your <hi>Names</hi> in the <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> do beſpeak; Chriſtians, know, that to be called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> is a <hi>Priviledge,</hi> but withal it is laden with duty, your Name in <hi>Chriſts Roll</hi> doth ſignifie your <hi>Ingagement</hi> to be for him, to follow him as his <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ldiers,</hi> to <hi>Fight under his Bunner</hi> and no other, to wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on him at all Times, and in all places and wayes of his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there to be ready to Anſwer to your <hi>Names</hi> when called, and upon the <hi>Intimation</hi> of any Service to be do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e for him to ſay (as he <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.) <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> am I ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Woe to him that in a <hi>Profeſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> aims only at a <hi>Name,</hi> (as they <hi>Iſai.</hi> 4. 1.) <hi>to take away his Reproach,</hi> or gain a little Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute in the World. Either appear in the work of Chriſt, or Cut thy <hi>Name</hi> out of the <hi>Liſt.</hi> Chriſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100070:24"/> will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat long, be ſure not alwayes with Chriſtians in <hi>Name</hi> only; but as you <hi>Souldiers</hi> do one of another, ſo will Chriſt require of you the Service and duty of your places. But if you are alive only in <hi>Name</hi> and dead to the work of your Calling, expect to be judged by <hi>Martial Law;</hi> and be ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e you will fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt very ſharp againſt <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> When you come into the Field <hi>compleatly armed,</hi> let your Arms about you make you turn to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. where you have the <hi>Armor</hi> ſet down that every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> muſt put on, and ſee if you have it all, and alſo if it be well fixed, and you thereby ready for Service. To want any piece of <hi>Armor,</hi> or to have any of that which he hath either <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſightly</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>unſerviceable</hi> will be as <hi>ridiculous</hi> and <hi>abſurd</hi> for the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> as the <hi>Souldier.</hi> Chriſt will have your <hi>Armor</hi> viewed to ſee if you have all your <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rements,</hi> according to <hi>Law,</hi> be ſo fixt that you may not be afraid of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Teſt.</hi> When commanded to fall into your places, think how ill Chriſt will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake it to find you ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and that either from ignorance of them, or unwillingneſs to be brought into, or kept in them; you have, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Souldiers, your Order, your diſtance to be obſerved, even <hi>Ranks,</hi> or <hi>streight kiles</hi> are often called for among you, (and perhaps no oftner then there is cauſe enough) obſerving your right-hand men is alſo required, with many the like, which make you a <hi>ſight</hi> comely in the eye of your Friends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>terrible</hi> to your <hi>Adverſaries.</hi> Now know, that <hi>all things</hi> in Chriſts Army are to be <hi>done decently and in order,</hi> (1 Cor. 14. 40.) and what is <hi>orderly</hi> will be <hi>decent.</hi> Each one hath his particular place, <hi>peculiar ſtation,</hi> and his <hi>proper work</hi> in that place or ſtation <hi>aſſigned</hi> to him, and that not only as referring to our ſelves, <hi>abſolute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>red,</hi> but <hi>relatively</hi> alſo, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> concerned with others among whom we walk. Beware of looking into other mens duties, ſo as to overlook our own: and yet again remember, we are our <hi>Brethrens keepers,</hi> and are ſo farr alſo to eye and obſerve them, that if they do well, we may imitate them, if otherwiſe, we may be <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to reform them by ſetting a better Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. <hi>Keeping thy Heart with all diligence,</hi> and making <hi>ſtreight ſteps</hi> to thy feet, (<hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 25, 27.) are directions that their <hi>Parra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> in <hi>Souldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry</hi> may bring to <hi>Remembrance.</hi> While you begin your <hi>Exerciſes</hi> with Prayers, (as you do if <hi>Chriſtian Souldiers</hi>) Remember that Scripture, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 6. and be <hi>practically convinced</hi> of the need of Prayer, <hi>all manner of Prayer,</hi> Epheſ. 6. 18. which he adds unto their being armed. When we mean that a Child is dead born, we ſay it's <hi>ſtill-born</hi> becauſe living Children uſually come into the World <hi>crying,</hi> thou mayeſt have a <hi>Name</hi> of being <hi>new born,</hi> but be ſure thou art dead, if thou do not pray, and <hi>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egular,</hi> if thou do it not in all the Seaſons of it, and that <hi>with all manner of Prayer</hi> too, ſee 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 17. with <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ph.</hi> 6. 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Prayer ſhould be an <hi>Introduction</hi> to work, and be ſure matter will ſucceed with thee in the Warr, according as the Hand of Prayer is up or down <hi>Ex.</hi> 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. You are often commanded <hi>ſilence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> (and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s pity there ſhould be ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100070:24"/> often need of <hi>commanding</hi> it, there being ever need of <hi>attending</hi> it, as that without which no other word of Command can be obeyed, becauſe not heard and underſtood, &amp; <hi>Solomo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eccl.</hi> 9. 17. will tell you <hi>that the words of the wiſe are heard in Silence;</hi> Chriſtians, let your Souls be ſilent and ſtill before the Lord, <hi>Commune with your own Hearts &amp; be ſtill,</hi> Pſal 4. 4. that you may liſten to what God ha's to ſay to you. The <hi>noiſe</hi> and <hi>Dinn</hi> of <hi>car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al reaſonings, worldly luſts,</hi> and <hi>Buſineſſes, immoderate deſires</hi> after <hi>lawful things,</hi> with inordinate ones after <hi>unlawful,</hi> theſe and ſuch like make ſuch a <hi>Clamour</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> in mens ears that <hi>Gods v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ice</hi> is not heard by them, and ſo they bring themſelves into a <hi>Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> for want of knowing and underſtanding the word of Command. Keep in a <hi>ſtill, quiet poſture,</hi> then ſit to hear and obey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face to your Leader,</hi> is a word of Command you often hear of alſo, and you have one <hi>General Command</hi> for all, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2. that you ſhould do all your <hi>motions</hi> with your <hi>Face</hi> to your <hi>Leader,</hi> run your whole<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Race looking to Jeſus.</hi> A look to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> gives both direction how, and <hi>ſtrength</hi> where with to <hi>run, work, Fight.</hi> Keeping your eye <hi>Chriſt-ward,</hi> will be of more <hi>Advantage</hi> to you in your <hi>Combat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> then either <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>wind</hi> which <hi>Combatans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> have ſo much regard to. A <hi>new look to Jeſus</hi> will give <hi>new leggs</hi> to <hi>run, new hands</hi> and <hi>Skill</hi> to <hi>Fight,</hi> and a <hi>conſtant Facing Chriſt-ward</hi> will keep you in a <hi>righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Fighting,</hi> and ſo <hi>overcoming poſture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when ſo <hi>Facing,</hi> you are bidden <hi>march,</hi> mind your Duty of <hi>preſſing on forward,</hi> (Phil. 3. 14.) you muſt <hi>move</hi> and <hi>promove</hi> in your <hi>Chriſtian Courſe,</hi> yea, and let your eyes look <hi>ſtreight on,</hi> and <hi>right forward,</hi> without turning to the <hi>right hand</hi> or the <hi>left Prov.</hi> 4. 25, 27. And while you <hi>follow</hi> him as your <hi>Leader,</hi> where ever he goes, you are ſure to <hi>goe right,</hi> and certain not to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any difficulty, out of which he will not alſo lead you in the End. This <hi>Leader</hi> never <hi>miſleads</hi> any that <hi>follow him.</hi> All your <hi>lawful Facings</hi> are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and marches after him. Beware of <hi>Confuſion</hi> in your <hi>Counter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> it is dangerous to ſee <hi>Chriſtians</hi> march <hi>Counter,</hi> but a pleaſant thing to ſee them all minding the ſame things, and moving the ſame way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stand</hi>] in <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to <hi>going back</hi> by <hi>ſinful diſcouragements</hi> or <hi>forward</hi> by <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ddy preſumption. Stand your Ground,</hi> and <hi>maintain</hi> it againſt <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Satan, give no place</hi> to either. Let no <hi>Oppoſition</hi> fright you into a <hi>Retreat, Gods Soul takes no pleaſure in them that draw back,</hi> or <hi>give out,</hi> Heb. 10 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Stand ſtill,</hi> you muſt, <hi>to ſee the Salvation of God,</hi> Ekod 14. 13. Only know, your Time to <hi>ſtand,</hi> and your Time to <hi>Advance,</hi> and know, that you have no Time to <hi>Fall back.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As you were</hi>] if ſpoken to men in a <hi>Rout</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> now, who were ſometimes in <hi>Order,</hi> is good, and is the Summe of this word of Advice, from Chriſt to <hi>Epheſus</hi> Rev. 2. 4. 5. where they are minded of the lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of their <hi>firſt love,</hi> and willed to <hi>remember from whence they are fallen and do their firſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100070:25"/> works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> from which Text we had a <hi>ſolemn word</hi> from the Lord by the mouth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Servant in our late <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> the Lord grant that it may be received, remembred and attended a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the voice of Chriſt, and happy <hi>New-England,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alter all our diſorders, we may at laſt <hi>rally,</hi> and be [<hi>as we were</hi>] in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> [<hi>as you were</hi>] be taken for men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being in the ſame Condition that they have been long agone, after much Time ſpent, and many means uſed for their <hi>bettering,</hi> if ſtill they are <hi>Ignorant</hi> as they were, <hi>Scepticks</hi> as they were, <hi>forma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ighty,</hi> or <hi>Superficial</hi> as they were, <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>profane</hi> as they were, or ſuch it may alſo be ſaid, they are <hi>Fools</hi> as they were, <hi>Children</hi> as they were, <hi>Sluggards</hi> as they were, turning like the door upon the <hi>Hinges,</hi> doing without any thing done, moving without any <hi>progreſs,</hi> and are themſelves in a <hi>perillous Condition,</hi> being ſome of them that help to make <hi>perilious Times,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 7. <hi>ever learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Make good your Leaders Ground</hi>] A <hi>ſeaſonable word</hi> of Command for the <hi>riſing Generation</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi> Could we be with God as our <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> were, he would be with us as he was with our <hi>Fathers.</hi> Did not our <hi>Fathers do Juſtice and Judgement,</hi> and it was well with them? <hi>Jer.</hi> 22. 15, 16. To imitate them will be our <hi>prudence,</hi> and <hi>weal. God remembers the kindneſs</hi> of <hi>our youth,</hi> then was <hi>New-England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lineſs to the Lord,</hi> as <hi>Jer. 2. 1-3. Our Fathers found no iniquity in God</hi> to give them any occaſion to change their God, or the wayes of ſerving and worſhipping their God. The ſame God ſhould be ours, and he is the ſame, and his wayes the ſame. <hi>Gadding</hi> to <hi>change</hi> our <hi>way</hi> will not pleaſe him. We are in a way of <hi>Reformation,</hi> if God diſcovers to us farther then to them that were before us, <hi>thankfully improve</hi> that <hi>light,</hi> only let that Ground which they gained (for which alſo they had <hi>Scripture-Ground</hi>) be <hi>firſt maintained</hi> or <hi>made good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Beat</hi> of the <hi>Drum,</hi> the <hi>Sound</hi> of the <hi>Trumpet</hi> is of <hi>great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> to <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and to <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as much, Know, that God alſo calls you to hearken to the <hi>Sound</hi> of the <hi>Trumpet,</hi> Jer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17. <hi>viz.</hi> his voice in his word, and that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the publick diſpenſing of it by his <hi>Watch-men,</hi> whoſe work it is to <hi>lift up their voice a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Trumpet.</hi> Then when the <hi>Trumpet</hi> is <hi>blown,</hi> do you <hi>attend,</hi> Amos 3. 6. yea, and bleſs God that it is not your portion to dwell there, where the <hi>Trumpet</hi> gives an <hi>uncertain Sound,</hi> 1 Cor. 14 8. <hi>File-Leaders</hi> (as well as <hi>chief Leaders</hi>) ſee how you lead, have a Care to go right, leſt you miſlead others, &amp; their <hi>miſcarriages</hi> be charged to your <hi>account.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Examples of <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding men</hi> are <hi>leading Examples,</hi> and if bad Examples then <hi>miſleading</hi> once too. <hi>Peters Example</hi> before others, was in a Senſe <hi>Coercive</hi> or <hi>compelling</hi> to them. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 13, 14.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Souldiers</hi> you ſet your <hi>Watch,</hi> and place your <hi>Sentinels,</hi> and I am ſure, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Chriſtians</hi> you have as much need, while you are in the <hi>Enemies Country,</hi> or he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100070:25"/> in your<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The Enemy lies <hi>intrenched</hi> within view, you had need <hi>keep your hearts with all diligence,</hi> and often <hi>walk the Rounds,</hi> as <hi>careful Commanders</hi> will in perſon do, walk up and down the World with your Soules under neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and <hi>Conſcientious Obligations</hi> to Attend that duty, ſo frequently and ſolemnly urged in the Scriptures, ſee 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 8. with <hi>Mark</hi> 13. 33, 37.</p>
               <p>When you are commanded to <hi>Charge, preſent, give fire,</hi> it is a ſhame and trouble to you to <hi>miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Fire,</hi> or make only <hi>falſe Fire,</hi> or when a mark is before you not to hitt: it think then how it offends Chriſt, <hi>diſadvantages</hi> you now, and will grieve you another day, if the reſult of all your <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded preparation</hi> hath only been a <hi>little falſe Fire,</hi> a <hi>form of Godlineſs</hi> an <hi>empt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Then be ſure to be well f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xed, and take <hi>good Aim,</hi> be not like a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Bow, do not ſhoot at Rovers, leſt you mils the Mark and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe the great Prize, which as Profeſſors of the Name of Chriſt, you pretend to be labouring after</p>
               <p>In Summe it will be your Honour as Souldiers to be accurate and punctual in all your poſtures and Exerciſes; and it will your great Advantage as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans if you can (and you ſee if you will you may) turn all your Exerciſes into Spiritual and ſpecial uſe.</p>
               <p>Whether any of you may ever be called as <hi>Souldiers,</hi> to make matter to fill up the <hi>Pages</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Hipories</hi> with your <hi>warlike Exploits &amp; valorous deeds</hi> in taking of <hi>Cities, overrunning Countries,</hi> &amp;c. we know not; but if you be good <hi>Soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iers</hi> of Chriſt in the <hi>Spiritual warfare,</hi> that is the way to <hi>laſting honour.</hi> He t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at <hi>rules</hi> his own <hi>Spirit,</hi> is better, and ſhall be more <hi>honoured</hi> and <hi>rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> then he that <hi>wins</hi> a <hi>City,</hi> Prov. 16. 32.</p>
               <p>Only this you muſt all know that both as <hi>Souldiers &amp; Chriſtians</hi> your ſtrength &amp; Succeſs lies in <hi>the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> not in your ſelves. Truſt not to your <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſtrength, Activity Courage,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Battel</hi> is not alwayes to the <hi>ſtrong,</hi> not the <hi>Race</hi> to the <hi>ſwift,</hi> Eccl. 9. 11. man is not <hi>ſaved</hi> by his <hi>Strength,</hi> an <hi>Horſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a vain thing,</hi> Pſal. 33. 16. 17. In every <hi>Ingagement</hi> as <hi>men,</hi> as <hi>Souldiers,</hi> as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> there may be enough of our own <hi>weakneſs</hi> ſeen to <hi>humble</hi> us, and in all our <hi>Succeſs</hi> enough of <hi>Chriſts Power</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> to occaſion us to <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve him all the Glory.</hi> You are never like to have <hi>better Proſperity</hi> in either <hi>Warfare,</hi> then when you go forth <hi>ſenſible</hi> of your own <hi>Impotency,</hi> becauſe you then <hi>fairly</hi> and <hi>profeſſedly</hi> leave <hi>Room</hi> for him to <hi>advance</hi> his own <hi>Honour.</hi> ſee 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 12. And be ſure, when we come to ſee how our matters were brought about, we ſhall ſet the <hi>Crown</hi> on the <hi>Head of Chriſt,</hi> and throw down our own <hi>Crown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> at his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eet.</p>
               <p>To conclude with a word of that which ſhall ſhortly put a Concluſion to all our <hi>Exerciſes</hi> in this World whether <hi>Military, Civil,</hi> or <hi>Religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi> Know, that <hi>Death our Enemy</hi> is upon a <hi>ſwift</hi> and <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eedy march</hi> towards us, and we are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening toward him, and therefore muſt <hi>neceſſarily</hi> meet quickly, between this
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100070:26"/> and that the Time is but ſhort, over a few dayes (<hi>moments</hi> it may be) the day will diſcover what we have been, and done. We are now all of us <hi>training <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p</hi> under the <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the <hi>Lords Houſe,</hi> and poſſibly (yea, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) in this Life he may put us to the Trial what we have gained, ſome ſuch <hi>plunge</hi> we may be brought unto, as wherein we ſhall have occaſion to uſe all the Skill that ever we have had an opportunity of getting. He may call us to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate</hi> with <hi>Perſecution, Poverty, Reprodeh, Bereavements of Relations</hi> &amp;c. or at the utmoſt <hi>Death</hi> will try us all, <hi>Death,</hi> (I ſay,) which among men of all <hi>Ages</hi> and <hi>Sexes</hi> takes <hi>promiſcuouſly</hi> according to the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> which the <hi>Lord of Life and Death</hi> hath given it, though ordinarily, thoſe that are in the <hi>Front</hi> are nextly for preſent Service, who <hi>diſcharge,</hi> and <hi>Fall off,</hi> and make way for the next to be <hi>Front.</hi> So <hi>one Generation paſſeth away, and another comes in its Room,</hi> Eccl. 1. 4. ever in motion, going off, and coming on the <hi>ſtage</hi> each hour and moment. I may not unfitly liken the <hi>whole Race of Man-kind,</hi> or all the men in the world to a <hi>well-Marſhall'd Army, (well-Marſhall'd</hi> I ſay, for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the <hi>ſeeming,</hi> and in themſelves <hi>real Confuſions</hi> that there are, the Lord orders all <hi>wiſely,</hi> and at the end will diſcover when all is put together, <hi>beautifully</hi> too) upon a <hi>march</hi> to meet with <hi>Death,</hi> where the <hi>firſt Rank diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge,</hi> (yea, and are <hi>diſcharged</hi> too) <hi>Fall off,</hi> yea, <hi>Fall down,</hi> never to return or riſe more, and then the next is firſt, and ſo on; there are <hi>Old men, middle-Aged,</hi> and <hi>young ones,</hi> in the <hi>Front, Center,</hi> and <hi>Rear</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> The <hi>Old Fall off,</hi> the <hi>middle-Aged Advance,</hi> the <hi>Younger</hi> are <hi>drawing</hi> after, now, though ſometimes here and there one of the <hi>younger ones</hi> may be pickt out of the <hi>Reer</hi> by a Shott out of <hi>Deaths murthering piece,</hi> yet we commonly ſay, and truly, <hi>Young ones may die, but Old ones muſt.</hi> It's a uſual word of Command among you, <hi>The firſt Rank <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake ready,</hi> they eſpecially ſhould be ready, but it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a duty for us all to <hi>watch and pray alwayes,</hi> that we may be <hi>accounted wort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to ſtand when the Son of man ſhall come. Let all our <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>motions</hi> through out our whole Life tend to the fitting us for a <hi>ſafe, Honourable, and comfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Exit</hi> at laſt, that when we come to look <hi>Death</hi> in the <hi>Face,</hi> or to <hi>look back<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> (and we ſhould often <hi>look back</hi>) upon our <hi>Life paſt,</hi> we may neither be <hi>afraid,</hi> nor <hi>aſhamed to die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But perhaps ſome may think that I have <hi>Charged</hi> too farr and that it is Time to <hi>draw off,</hi> I ſhall therefore immediately <hi>diſcharge</hi> you of your <hi>preſent Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance;</hi> Only that I may not leave you within fight of <hi>Death</hi> without a <hi>Prayer</hi> for you, give me leave in ſo many words, to cloſe with my Deſires on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. (<hi>&amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am nil niſi vota ſuperſunt</hi>)</p>
               <p>In general, my wiſhes for you are, that you may be <hi>bleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of the Lord, and from the Houſe of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More particularly,</p>
               <p>That the Lord will <hi>bleſs your Labours, accept your work,</hi> Ecci. 9. 7. continue
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100070:26"/> and increaſe both your <hi>Number</hi> and Skill, that he will <hi>teach your hands to Warr, and your fingers to Fight,</hi> Pſal. 144. 1. grant that your <hi>thoughts, words,</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> in this Affair eſpecially, <hi>may be acceptable to him;</hi> and may you have all Incouragement and Countenance from men too.</p>
               <p>That the Lord will make you all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as well as <hi>Souldiers,</hi> yea, <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Christians,</hi> and <hi>accurate Souldiers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That if it be beſt for his <hi>Glory,</hi> the <hi>Common good,</hi> and your <hi>particular weal</hi>) you may not be uſed in any other <hi>Military way</hi> then in this that you are in, of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</hi> You honour God in the uſe of this means of his Appointment to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for <hi>Warr,</hi> and he can honour you by preventing any further uſe of this <hi>preparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That if the Lord hath further occaſion for you, he will make you <hi>offer your ſelves willingly,</hi> yea, though it be to the <hi>jeoparding of your Lives to the Death i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the High places of the Field,</hi> Judg. 5. 2, 9, 18.</p>
               <p>And then that <hi>the Lord of Hosts</hi> himſelf will encourage your Hearts, <hi>ſtrengthen your hands and cover your Heads in the day of Battel,</hi> Pſal. 140. 7. And <hi>Gods preſence wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h you,</hi> together with the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> while you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Advice, will both <hi>put</hi> and <hi>maintain valour</hi> in you, and be a <hi>ſafe protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> over you.</p>
               <p>Finally, for your ſelves, and all of us here preſent, (your <hi>Fellow-Souldiers</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian warf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re</hi>) let us beg that when we come to lay down our Arms at the <hi>Grave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> and there to take ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>final diſcharge</hi> from all kind of Warr, we may be able <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach for himſelf to ſay with ſome of our <hi>latest Breath,</hi> in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of that <hi>Good old Souldier of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Tim. 4 7. <hi>I have fought a good Fight, I have finiſhed my Courſe, I have kept the Faith. Henceforth there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> laid up for me a Crown of Life, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give me a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that Day, and not to me only, but to all them alſo that love his appearing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
